<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The foundation of God, with the immutability thereof laid for the salvation of his elect; with infallible marks and signs of election. Which may serve as a storehouse of comfort to religious minds, in this season of danger felt and feared.</title>
            <author>Crompton, William, 1633-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80867</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7031A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896143</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896143</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153887</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80867)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153887)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2387:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The foundation of God, with the immutability thereof laid for the salvation of his elect; with infallible marks and signs of election. Which may serve as a storehouse of comfort to religious minds, in this season of danger felt and feared.</title>
                  <author>Crompton, William, 1633-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 131, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for James Cowse bookseller in Exeter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reissue, with cancel title page and added dedication leaf (pi1-2), of the edition with "printed for Robert Clavell" in imprint (Wing C7031A).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Election (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>God --  Attributes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153887:1"/>
            <p>THE FOUNDATION OF GOD, WITH THE Immutability thereof, Laid for the Salvation of his <hi>Elect;</hi> with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Marks and Signs of <hi>Election.</hi> Which may ſerve as a Storehouſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to Religious Minds, in this Seaſon of Danger felt and feared.</p>
            <q>As many as were ordained to eternal Life, believed,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 13.48.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>The Highway of the upright is to depart from evil,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 16.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>We are kept by the Power of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Pet. 1.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Cowſe</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Exeter.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153887:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153887:2"/>
            <p>To the Honoured The Lady <hi>Suſanna Holworthy; William Crompton</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel,</p>
            <p>Dedicateth the following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, of the Perpetuity of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate mans Eſtate.</p>
            <p>In oppoſition to that pernicious Doctrine of the Saints Apoſtacy;</p>
            <p>As a Teſtimony of the great Honour and Service ſo juſtly due from him, and all that know her.</p>
            <p>Preſuming on her perſeverance in Grace and Title to Glory.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153887:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153887:3"/>
            <p>THE FOUNDATION OF GOD, WITH THE Immutability thereof, Laid for the Salvation of his <hi>Elect;</hi> with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Marks and Signs of <hi>Election.</hi> Which may ſerve as a Storehouſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to Religious Minds, in this Seaſon of Danger felt and feared.</p>
            <q>As many as were ordained to eternal Life, believed,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 13.48.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>The Highway of the upright is to depart from evil,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 16.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>We are kept by the Power of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Pet. 1.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard, 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:153887:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153887:4"/>
            <head>THE FOUNDATION OF GOD, With the Immutability thereof, Laid for the Salvation of his <hi>Elect,</hi> with the Infallible Marks and Signs of <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> &amp;c. From</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Tim. 2.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs, the foundation of God ſtands ſure, having this Seal, the Lord knoweth who are his; and let every one that nameth the name of Chriſt depart from Iniquity.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Pen-men of Sacred Scripture, in their ſeveral diſcourſes, had propoſed to them theſe ends, <hi>viz.</hi> to publiſh the Truth impartially; to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Sin and Errours boldly; to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153887:5"/>the Elect, and to perſuade all men in their ſeveral Callings to walk con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably.</p>
            <p>All which are obſerved exactly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very-where, by our Apoſtle; more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in theſe Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy,</hi> in this Chapter and Text, moſt pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually.</p>
            <p>Neither may I propoſe unto my ſelf any other ends in Preaching or Writing it, than St. <hi>Paul</hi> did in penning it; <hi>viz.</hi> to explain the truth of Chriſt hid from many; to ſuppreſs, by endeavour, Sin and falſe Opinions; to comfort the deſpiſed Flock; to chear up their droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souls againſt dangers felt and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and to perſuade all that <hi>name the Name of Chriſt, to depart from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the more eaſie entrance upon the Text, we will ſee the whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter briefly analyzed: wherein we find divers Exhortations of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> and in him to the whole Church of God. As,</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153887:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> to be valiant, chearful and careful in the Grace and Work of Chriſt; both to teach perſonally, and ordain men fit and able, faithfully to reach others, <hi>Ver.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>It ſhould be our meat and drink to do the Will of him, that hath ſet us on work.</p>
            <p>Gods Ordinances ſuffer by irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities; and therefore Church Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours muſt be careful not to permit unlearned and irreligious men to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the Miniſterial Office; who, like the ſons of <hi>Eli,</hi> forſaking the Character of their Dignity, will bring contempt upon the Divine Oblations, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> patiently to undergo the burden of his Office, in the pains and ſorrows neceſſarily attending thereon, <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. Miniſters may not expect al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to ſee <hi>Halcyon</hi>-days, nor the ſhines of worldly favour. <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Silver Age, like the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> comes rarely. Though their work be full of Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet its full of danger. Miniſters
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153887:6"/>are Stars, but will be often muffled in Clouds; they are Lights, but ſhall meet with many Winds, which ſhall be apt to blow them out. <hi>Luther</hi> ſpake too true, when he ſaid, That to be a faithful Preacher and not meet with troubles, is impoſſible. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil will raiſe up the whole <hi>Militia</hi> of Hell againſt them; and therefore, of all men, ſuch have need, as of Courage ſo of Patience.</p>
            <p>Of this he gives two reaſons; <hi>One</hi> drawn from the bond between them and Chriſt, as between a Soldier and his Captain; who muſt ſtay not only in the fair and ſoft march, but in the hot and bloody Battle. The <hi>other,</hi> from the Reward, implied in two Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes; the firſt from a <hi>Wreſtler,</hi> who ſtriving lawfully, ſhall be crown'd; <hi>Ver.</hi> 5. The ſecond of an <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who after a ſtormy Winter, ſhall ſee the moſt deſireably pleaſant Spring. The labour of none ſo intolerable, the reward of none ſo incomparable as of faithful Miniſters.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153887:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To defend two main Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtian Religion, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Incarnation</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of our Lord and Saviour, which were ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſed in thoſe early times of the Church, the Age immediately follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. In the 8th <hi>Ver.</hi> Theſe may be called the Pillars of Chriſtianity; the <hi>Articuli ſtantis vel cadentis Eccleſiae</hi> (as <hi>Luther</hi> ſpake in reference to the Doctrine of Juſtification by faith;) and mainly oppoſed by Hereticks and Seducers. Care muſt be taken to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them with vehemency and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Contention; and therefore the great Apoſtle would have <hi>Timothy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtir himſelf about theſe Points, and ſets on his advice with a ſpecial <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento,</hi> Remember, a word that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports both Affection and Action.</p>
            <p>From hence he proceeds to take off an Objection of fear, which might be raiſed in the mind of <hi>Timothy,</hi> (a young Steerſman in his new Office of an Evangeliſt and Lanched out into the deep, when Winds were loud and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153887:7"/>ſeas went high) by reaſon of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and perſecutions which would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly overtake him for the ſame truth; in <hi>Ver.</hi> 9.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> telling him,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That though he were bound, yet the <hi>Word of God was not bound,</hi> nor could be from working. Men may as ſoon fetter up the influence of the Sun, ſtop the motion of the Stars and hinder the blowing of Winds: or, whoever be bound, the Word of the Lord ſhall run and be glorified, have a prevailing Power. St. <hi>Paul</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed though a Priſoner, and ſo did other Martyrs in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the end of thoſe ſufferings would be every way profitable. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Word</hi> would be more effectual; as when <hi>Paul</hi> ſuffered, the Goſpel was further'd; <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.12; the <hi>Elect</hi> more couragious; ſo, <hi>the Brethren became hold by his bonds, and were bound to ſpeak the Word without fear:</hi> and the ſufferers more ſure of reigning with Chriſt, who went before them in the ſame path, from the Croſs to Paradiſe,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153887:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>from ſuffering to glory. <hi>It became him to ſuffer and enter into glory;</hi> and it becomes his Servants to follow their Lord. Beſides, all thoſe who for fear ſhall deny Chriſt, or his truth, <hi>here,</hi> ſhall be denied entrance into Heaven by Chriſt, <hi>hereafter.</hi> He is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a Crown, that dares not bleed to obtain it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He enjoyns him to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and oppoſe all Verbal Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies; <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. and doubtful Diſputes, becauſe of ſome evil conſequents which ordinarily follow thereupon; as</p>
            <p n="1">1. No profit to any: and therefore as the Shell-fiſh amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> was accounted <hi>unclean,</hi> becauſe it had little meat, and required a great deal of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to get it; ſo may they be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, who feed upon hard Queſtions and unprofitable Diſcourſes; and to as little purpoſe as thoſe in <hi>Rober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Gallus</hi> his Dream, who laying aſide the pure Manchet, fed upon hard ſtones, and ſo had little nouriſhment at the Feaſt. Niceties and Criticiſms
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153887:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>in Religion taking up Mens thoughts, Faith and Holineſs are neglected, and and ſo they labour about a Shell-fiſh, pick Bones and feed not on Meat.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Subverſion of the Hearers.</p>
            <p>Miniſters therefore, ſhould ſtudy to divide the Word aright, applying it to the capacity of their Hearers; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masking the Truth, that each Eye may ſee and every Soul be enamour'd with its beauty, ſhunning as profane, <hi>Ver.</hi> 16. ſo affected terms and curious expreſſions, which with their paint and meretricious bravery, keep out the light of ſolid Truth. That's the beſt Glaſs which moſt truly ſhews the face, not that which is richly ſet with Pearls; and that's the beſt preaching, which hath moſt to do with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; which hath <hi>plus operis quam oſtentationis,</hi> and ſpeaks to the Ears of that which St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den man of the heart;</hi> to which, the <hi>Plain-ſong</hi> always makes the beſt Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153887:8"/>Such was the practice of that <hi>Golden-mouth</hi> of the Weſt, of zealous Mr. <hi>Bradford</hi> and the renowned <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that he came ſo cloſe in his Applications, that he was almoſt able to make his Hearers hearts fall down within them.</p>
            <p>This Evil here rebuked, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares to a <hi>Gangrene,</hi> Ver. 17, which creeps from part to part, till the whole be infected. So it hath been with contentious Verbaliſts, ſophiſtical Wranglers; who ſtudy more for words than matter, and dote more on a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm, than on a practical truth, catch more after an Elegancy than a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
            <p>For Example, he brings in <hi>Hyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> and <hi>Philetus;</hi> ſhewing firſt their Opinion about the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> V. 18. and then the danger of it, <hi>overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faith of ſome.</hi> It muſt needs be a ſtrange Opinion indeed, that none will follow; and ſcarce any ſo monſtrous, but if it hath had a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, will alſo find a Nurſe. <hi>Many
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153887:9"/>ſhall follow their pernicious ways.</hi> A ſad judgment upon them, who receive not <hi>the truth</hi> in <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> He endeavours to remove the offence might ariſe from the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away of ſuch, <hi>Ver.</hi> 19, 20, 21. ſhewing,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Gods Elect were exempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from that danger; being fixt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveably in their Orb, like glittering and never falling Stars; Their <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> being of God, not in, or of themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How Chriſtians might be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of their <hi>Election;</hi> than which there could be no greater comfort on this ſide Heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That there ever have been, are and will be a mixt multitude in the Church (the Moon hath her ſpots, and clouds are among the ſtars;) comparing it to a great Houſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are <hi>Veſſels of gold,</hi> appointed to <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi> and of <hi>wood,</hi> appointed to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour. Veſſels of gold and ſilver,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying diverſity of gifts in the <hi>Elect:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153887:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Veſſels of wood and earth,</hi> ſhewing a difference of ſin in <hi>Reprobates.</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Gold,</hi> muſt not run from thoſe of <hi>Wood;</hi> God is and will be glorified in both. No final ſeparating from the true Church, becauſe of wicked men, <hi>Veſſels of diſhonour</hi> therein. As God doth not, ſo neither muſt man pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the innocent for the nocent; <hi>I flye from the chaff, leſt I ſhould be ſuch,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtin; I forſake not the floor, leſt I ſhould be nothing.</hi> Which conſideration, ſhould ſerve to qualifie the exceſſive heat of ſome among us, who are <hi>zealous, but not according to knowledg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> He exhorts to a peaceable profeſſion of <hi>Holineſs;</hi> ſhewing how Miniſters ſhould behave themſelves in the Church, to work this in the hearts of people; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſhun <hi>youthful Luſts.</hi> So call'd, becauſe <hi>youth</hi> is moſt ſubject to them. Neither are we men in Chriſt, till we have in ſome meaſure ſubdued them. Underſtanding here, the <hi>Luſt</hi> of <hi>ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:153887:10"/>boaſting, and vain-glory; not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding other evil motions of <hi>Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To <hi>follow Righteouſneſs,</hi> Faith and Charity; in ſtudy, conference and diſputation; that ſo, fooliſh and unlearned Queſtions, may be ever diſtaſteful to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. With <hi>meekneſs and gentleneſs</hi> to reprove ſuch as go aſtray, eſpecially on the right-hand, <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Set them in joint again:</hi> ſo that Text runs. Reprehenſion is not an act of <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery,</hi> but of <hi>Chyrurgery;</hi> and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters muſt do as Chyrurgions uſe to do with broken bones and diſlocated joints, who reſtore them with ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs; patiently expecting the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of Divine goodneſs upon them in their Repentance. Who would wound thoſe, whom they deſign to cure? A word will do more with ſome, than a blow with others. Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right blows do not always pierce deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. Stormy ſpirits are not often ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious. It is not the ſparkling
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153887:10"/>flame, but inviſible heats, which melt metals. Furious proceedings do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten bind faſter; when a loving per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion upon certain grounds, reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers many from Satans ſnares.</p>
            <p>By this time, this occaſion of the words in hand is manifeſt. <hi>Hymenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> teach falſe Doctrine, and thereby ſeduce others after them; ſuch as had but a temporary faith and made an outward profeſſion without inward ſincerity. True juſtifying faith being an infuſed habit, cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, by any act or acts of men: that were to make the <hi>foundation</hi> void or uncertain and the building rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous: When the Apoſtle tells us plainly, the <hi>foundation of God ſtands ſure,</hi> &amp;c. Yet by the falling away of temporary Profeſſours, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men of eminence and worth; St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw or foreſaw, that good men were or might be offended.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Seeing Learned men fall away, they might begin to affect a change, to think or ſay, Why ſhould not we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153887:11"/>be of the ſame mind with them, they ſee more than we can or do?</p>
            <p n="2">2. They did or might fall foul on the Church: how can that be a true Church which breeds Hereticks; wherein are ſo many Sects and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions? Theſe are ſo many ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks in their way, producing ſuch ſcandals and prejudices in their minds, as cannot eaſily be removed: as the Papiſts do with much outrage object againſt the Reformed Churches, though they do it with many falſe ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When they ſaw men of great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and note in the Church to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy that faith which <hi>once</hi> they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, they began to doubt of the Churches continuance; of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God made unto it, or at leaſt, that there was no <hi>certainty</hi> of any thing therein; no aſſurance of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance to ſalvation in that Church, when ſuch great ones fall.</p>
            <p>To all, our Apoſtle here anſwers, that there was no ſuch cauſe of fear
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153887:11"/>or doubting: for although ſome of principal note, err, or be ſeduced and fall away, yet <hi>the foudation of God ſtands ſure, the Lord knows who are his,</hi> and none can <hi>pluck them out of his hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the Text is nothing elſe, but a comfortable concluſion againſt that damnable and Spirit-quenching doctrine of <hi>Saint-Apoſtacy;</hi> Which St. <hi>Paul</hi> might foreſee ſhould be broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the latter days, perſuading them then and all other true Churches of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That notwithſtanding <hi>Phygellus</hi> and <hi>Hermogenes, Hymenoeus</hi> and <hi>Phyletus; Pelagius, Bertius, Arminius, Thomſon, Jackſon, Mountague,</hi> with others ſince; Pope and Popelings with all their followers and abetters, have or ſhould err and ſeduce many after them; Yet we ſhould not be offended, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged; for the Elect of Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>finally</hi> be ſeduced, nor their faith deſtroyed <hi>totally,</hi> becauſe their ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is grounded upon the Eternal
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153887:12"/>and conſtant purpoſe of God; which <hi>foundation</hi> ſtands firmer than to be ſhaken with ſuch blaſts.</p>
            <p>The ſalvation of Chriſts <hi>Elect,</hi> hath a firm <hi>foundation;</hi> not in <hi>man,</hi> but in <hi>God;</hi> not wavering or undetermined, but <hi>ſtanding</hi> ſurely ſealed in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God; and that not only in the knowledg of <hi>ſimple intelligence,</hi> as poſſible, conditionally, if <hi>they</hi> will, or if ſuch and ſuch things fall out; but in the knowledg of <hi>pure Viſion,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly and eternally decreed to be certain; whereby the Lord particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly did and doth diſcern his own from others, calling them by their Names, and by his Embaſſadours ſhowing them the marks, whereby they may know their own <hi>Election.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parts of this Scripture are two, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The cauſe and certainty of the ſalvation of Gods Elect. <hi>The foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of God ſtandeth ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The marks and notes of <hi>Election,</hi> whereby men may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153887:12"/>aſſured, they are of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p>Here we have, what God did freely for his <hi>Elect</hi> before they were; What the <hi>Elect</hi> by Gods help muſt and will do for themſelves after they are.</p>
            <p>Of both theſe in their order; and firſt of the former, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The foundation of God.</q>
            <p>There is a two-fold <hi>foundation</hi> laid: One that is <hi>God;</hi> ſo the whole Trinity is <hi>a foundation</hi> to the being and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of all things. Chriſt Jeſus the ſecond Perſon in the Trinity is the <hi>foundation</hi> of Election and Salvation: <hi>Other foundation can no man lay than that which is laid, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.11. <hi>Another,</hi> that is <hi>of</hi> God; and ſo the foundation is two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of <hi>Creation;</hi> Gods intent and purpoſe to give a <hi>Being</hi> unto things, which, as then, had none: and this <hi>foundation</hi> remains ſure; <hi>One generation paſſeth away and another cometh, but the earth,</hi> i. e. the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153887:13"/>of the Creation, <hi>abideth for ever,</hi> Eccleſ. 1.4. And, <hi>whereupon are the foundations thereof founded,</hi> Job 38.6. And, <hi>who laid the foundations of the earth, that it ſhould not be removed for ever?</hi> Pſalm 104.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Of <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> his immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Decree and Purpoſe; diſpoſing all things created to their ſeveral ends. To which ends they muſt arrive <hi>by</hi> means. The means is Service to be performed here in this World. All ſerve him not alike; all were not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by him for one end. As the Love of God was not alike to all his Creatures in the <hi>foundation,</hi> ſo the ſervice of his Creatures is not all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. Some ſerve him <hi>neceſſarily, by</hi> natural inclination, as the Heavens and Elements, with all thoſe bright and purer Bodies contained in them, which run their courſe by the mighty Word of God's Power; they live by the Spirit's Omnipotency and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Acts, wherewith the <hi>Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> glorifies it ſelf: their end is to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153887:13"/>move and work for the good of man; after his departure hence, they ſhall be diſſolved; either by being renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſome other end, or annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Some ſerve him <hi>conſtrainedly,</hi> by unwitting ſubjection to his all-ruling Power: as all Reprobates, both An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men, effecting the Lords purpoſes by his co-active direction, not out of any good intention to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him: with whom he glorifies himſelf in his Juſtice; <hi>whoſe end is damnation!</hi> The Lord foreſeeing them in their bloud, paſt by them <hi>before time;</hi> they actually diſpoſe themſelves to deſtruction <hi>in time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others there are who ſerve him <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily,</hi> with <hi>purpoſe of heart,</hi> as ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men, made good by <hi>Election and effectual Vocation,</hi> whoſe end is <hi>ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> without poſſibility of failing, in reſpect of Gods <hi>foundation;</hi> whoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal purpoſe was, by ſuch means to bring them to ſuch an end: and with theſe God glorifies himſelf in reſpect
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153887:14"/>of his <hi>mercy.</hi> God can loſe no part of his glory, neither in regard of Power, Juſtice or Mercy (theſe glorious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes will ſhine, without an unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted or beſpotted ſplendour) therefore none of theſe can miſs their proper ends.</p>
            <p>To give an Example of this laſt. <hi>Hymenoeus and Paul, Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,</hi> were of the ſame matter, had the ſame power of Will, but Gods diſpoſition of them in the <hi>foundation,</hi> put a difference in their actual ſervice; two of them err and deſtroy the faith; the other, both preach the truth and build up the faith of many. Even ſo, all things created, were eternally in the ſecret Counſel of God, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and pre-ordained to their ſeveral ends by means, <hi>according to the good pleaſure of his Will;</hi> Whether to return to no being, to a worſe or a better-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and this, I conceive, is the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of God,</hi> here meant.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:153887:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <q>Standeth ſure.</q>
            <p>Immutable and inevitable. And that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Ex parte Dei,</hi> in regard of the Decree it ſelf; which knits together the end and means unſeparably. So that the Creature cannot but perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, in uſing the means to attain their pre-ordained ends: not ſo much by any Vertue connate or inherent in themſelves, or by any outward Agent <hi>violently</hi> impelling, but by the power of God, gently diſpoſing of what he finds in them, or beſtows upon them, according to his own purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Ex parte rei,</hi> in reſpect of the Subject of this <hi>foundation;</hi> elected ones after their effectual Calling, are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not by a <hi>direct</hi> act of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Will, aſſenting to the Work and Promiſe of God, but by <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection</hi> upon themſelves in ſpecial, do <hi>believe,</hi> believing <hi>apprehend,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending <hi>apply,</hi> and by applying are particularly <hi>aſſured,</hi> not only for the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153887:15"/>time preſent (which <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians</hi> may admit), but for the time to come, that they ſhall perſevere and be ſaved, by vertue of Gods free love and grace as the <hi>foundation,</hi> and by the meritorious ſufferings of Chriſt as the <hi>means</hi> of ſalvation. And this is the certainty here meant.</p>
            <q>Having this Seal.</q>
            <p>When <hi>Darius</hi> with his Lords had caſt <hi>Daniel</hi> into the Lions Den (<hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17.) the entrance was ſealed with the Kings own Signet and that of his Lords, that the purpoſe might not be changed concerning <hi>Daniel:</hi> ſo when the King of Heaven decreed to take up all his <hi>Daniels,</hi> his beloved ones, out of the Den of the roaring Lion, he put <hi>his Seal</hi> unto the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, that the purpoſe might not be chang'd or alter'd. This <hi>Seal</hi> is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> there is <hi>the Seal</hi> of God in <hi>Man,</hi> of which we ſhall be led to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153887:15"/>in managing the latter part of the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is the <hi>Seal</hi> of God unto this <hi>foundation</hi> in <hi>God, the Lord knoweth who are his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lords <hi>knowledg</hi> is infinite; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal as himſelf and infallible, from all Eternity fore-knowing all things that ever ſhould come to paſs; not by diſcourſe or ſucceſſion, as to know this by that, or that after this; nor by that metaphyſical manner of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by way of compoſition or Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which pre-ſuppoſes diſtinct acts for ſeveral Objects; but by one ſingle individual act (if we may lawfully ſpeak of ſo high a myſtery), fore-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and knowing every thing in <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> by way of Eminency; in their <hi>ſecond cauſes</hi> before they were, and in <hi>themſelves</hi> as if they had been; Univerſals and particulars, which were to be made or done, beeing laid before him from all Eternity, as if they had been already made or done. <hi>The Lord knows who are his,</hi> and who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153887:16"/>are not; but his own he knows with an eſpecial <hi>knowledg</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, as he doth not others: <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.12. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, I know you not.</hi> Therefore there is a <hi>book of Life;</hi> none of <hi>Death,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in Scripture: this <hi>book of Life,</hi> is this Knowledg here mentioned, wherein Gods own do ſtand firmly recorded. We know, this <hi>Knowledg</hi> of God is as himſelf, and can be no more divided than himſelf; yet for our better conceiving of things, ſo known by him, we diſtinguiſh of it. There is in God,</p>
            <p>Firſt, A <hi>neceſſary</hi> natural knowledg, which reſpects the <hi>Power</hi> and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, concerning all things done or poſſible to be done. This is not here meant.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A <hi>free knowledg,</hi> which goes hand in hand with the <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God,</hi> reſpecting only things that ſhould actually come to paſs with his approbation, and hath refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his <hi>mercy:</hi> and this is the knowledg here ſpoken of.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:153887:16"/>
            <p>The Lord knows with a free and everlaſting Knowledg, with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of <hi>Election and Reprobation,</hi> who were then decreed and ſhould ever remain to be his: ſo that ſuch men once ſo <hi>known,</hi> can never ceaſe to be his, or known to belong to any other. <hi>His</hi> may fall from themſelves and pluck off the <hi>Seal</hi> in themſelves, not from him, nor the <hi>Seal</hi> in him. <hi>None can pluck them out of my Fathers hands.</hi> Majeſty it ſelf may as ſoon be dethron'd, the Crown pluck'd from his Head who is the ſupreme King, and the golden Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter wreſted out of his hand; as ſoon may the <hi>Apple</hi> be pull'd out of his Eye, and the Deity annihilated, as the Elect be pulled out of Hands, as he be rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of one of his Jewels.</p>
            <p>This Knowledg goes along with the Decree; it ties together the Cauſe, the mean and the end; Election, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Juſtification both by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Righteouſneſs and imparted, with final ſalvation, which no force nor fraud, perſuaſion or temptation
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153887:17"/>can diſſolve or ſeparate. The will of his people being determined by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible grace; which way they ſhall <hi>neceſſarily</hi> yet <hi>freely</hi> diſpoſe of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, even in <hi>Conditional</hi> things.</p>
            <p>Which clearly overthrows that <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia media,</hi> invented by <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd by <hi>Arminians,</hi> whereby God ſhould fore-know, but leave the Will ſimply to it ſelf undetermined; ſo <hi>man</hi> in the choice of good ſhould be independent, give the praiſe and glory to himſelf, not to the free grace of God, diſpoſing the <hi>Will,</hi> to make a good choice. For, thoſe things which were to us contingents, or are offer'd to us conditionally, were certainly determined by this free knowledg of God, how they ſhould fall out, &amp; what we ſhould chuſe <hi>neceſſarily</hi> yet freely; gently ſubduing by his Spirit <hi>Reſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> in the Will, placing inſtead thereof, a ſenſe of the want and a ſecret longing after Grace.</p>
            <p>To manifeſt this <hi>Seal</hi> ſomewhat farther, this <hi>knowledg</hi> of God, the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153887:17"/>
               <hi>foundation</hi> (not only inchoative and terminatively, but diſpoſitive alſo) of our ſalvation, is, as we find in Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The eternal <hi>diſpoſing</hi> cauſe of all Events. The Will of God is the cauſe of all things, it ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſpeaks. Nothing now comes to paſs, but as he knew then it ſhould. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.28. <hi>Herod, Pontius, Gentiles and Jews, were gathered together, to do whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the hand and counſel of God had determined before to be done.</hi> All things have their futurition from his eternal Purpoſe: Whence alſo is in the eternal Mind the <hi>Idea</hi> of all things, with their circumſtances that ſhall be: <hi>that</hi> is the firſt Mover, continuing it ſelf immoveable, giving to every thing a regular motion, according to the impreſſion which it doth receive: <hi>for known are all his works, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world,</hi> Acts 15.18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is certain and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; <hi>the foundation ſtands ſure.</hi> Whom the Lord once Loves with this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153887:18"/>knowledg of approbation to be his, he loves and knows them ever. All his Saints are letters of Gold, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven on Chriſts heart, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be razed out. His Love is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Flame that no Water can quench. <hi>Nulloe ſunt lituroe in libro vitoe.</hi> His Book admits not of any <hi>Deleatur</hi> or expurgatory <hi>Index.</hi> God is ſo full of Light, as there is <hi>no ſhadow of change</hi> in him, <hi>Job</hi> 17.23. In that admirable Prayer made for the Church, Chriſt thus ſpeaks unto his Father; <hi>Thou haſt loved them, as thou haſt loved me.</hi> i. e. with a certain and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Love. If Chriſt can periſh and fall from the love of his Father, then may the <hi>Elect</hi> be ſeduced totally to fall away and periſh finally.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is of a certain number. The <hi>Lord knoweth who are his.</hi> Which cannot admit of any univerſal Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Gods intention. See <hi>Job</hi> 10.3. He knows his own ſheep ſo, as he <hi>calls them all by name.</hi> Job 13.18. <hi>I ſpeak not of you all, I know whom I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153887:18"/>have choſen.</hi> Revel. 7.4. <hi>I heard the number of them which were ſealed,</hi> &amp;c. Cap. 6.10, 11. <hi>They cried with a loud voice, ſaying,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and it was ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that they ſhould reſt for a little ſeaſon until their fellow-ſervants and their</hi> Brethren that ſhould be killed as they were, ſhould be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. From the Collation of which Texts, it may moſt eaſily be infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that their number is ſet and ſhall in due time be compleated: for that's the thing related unto in the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſhall be fulfilled.</hi> So certain is the number of the <hi>Elect,</hi> that one cannot be added, nor taken away; which could not be, without this pre-determining and preſent-diſpoſing knowledg of God. The beſt man in his pure naturals, would wholly caſt himſelf away, were he left to his own diſpoſe. Therefore ſufficiently-effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſaving grace is not univerſally of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to all men: Grace is not extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed beyond the Decree. Gods fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg limits both the end and the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153887:19"/>means: were the building larger than the <hi>foundation,</hi> it muſt needs prove ruinous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It is a free knowledg and foundation, not laid on any thing in us, either done or fore-ſeen to be done; but only the free-will and power of God. <hi>You have not choſen me, but I have choſen you.</hi> Called therefore it is, <hi>a fore-knowledg;</hi> paſt before we had done <hi>good or evil.</hi> Rom. 9.11. To clear this by a familiar inſtance or example; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a child may die before it had done either good or evil, this child was either elected or reprobated, without fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of either of good or evil <hi>actual;</hi> nothing he did, nothing therefore was fore-ſeen he ſhould do. If any reply, true, <hi>nothing</hi> was fore-ſeen he did, but ſomething he might have done, had he longer lived? The anſwer is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; This argument is prevented and cut off by the former diſtinction; Gods knowledg was of things that <hi>actually</hi> ſhould come to paſs, and not of things that <hi>might be</hi> only. St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,</hi> in his diſcourſe of <hi>Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> uſes three arguments to confirm
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153887:19"/>this truth in hand; ſharply condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Opinion of <hi>Pelagius</hi> and in him all <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Arminians</hi> at this day; concluding that the Lord choſe us not <hi>for</hi> faith, but <hi>to</hi> faith; he choſe not ſuch as were worthy, but by chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing made them worthy.</p>
            <p>The ſum of all may be collected in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one poſitive concluſion, or doctrinal Inſtruction, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="doctrine">
               <head>That there is a foundation laid in God, for the ſalvation of his Elect, that nothing can alter this foundation of God, ſeduce his Choſen finally from him, nor hinder them totally from aſſurance of ſalvation.</head>
               <p>Matth. 24.24. <hi>Falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, to ſeduce, if it were poſſible, the very Elect.</hi> If it were <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> implying, not a <hi>difficulty,</hi> as <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> would have it and the <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants</hi> expound it; but a reſeptive <hi>impoſſibility;</hi> as it will plainly appear to any, peruſing the Text impartially,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153887:20"/>with the circumſtances and intent of the Speaker. Falſe Chriſts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, with lying Signs and Wonders, ſhall deceive or ſeduce many; but for the <hi>Elect,</hi> that they ſhould be ſeduced, it is <hi>impoſſible,</hi> in reſpect of Gods im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable Purpoſe and Decree; Let them be of good comfort, <hi>the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtands ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there is ſuch a <hi>foundation,</hi> appears, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>According as he had choſen us in him, before the foundation of the world, that we ſhould be holy and without blame before him in love: having predeſtinated us with the adoption of children by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Rom. 8.29, 30. <hi>For whom he did fore-know, he alſo did predeſtinate to be conformed to the image of his Son,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>1 Theſſal. 5.9. <hi>For God hath not appointed us to unto wrath, but to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſalvation by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2 Tim. 1.9. <hi>Who hath ſaved us and called us with an holy Calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpoſe and grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153887:20"/>
               <p>Titus 1.12. — <hi>According to the faith of Gods elect — in hope of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, which God that cannot lye, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed before the world began.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That this <hi>foundation</hi> is <hi>ſure;</hi> ſee Pſalm 125. v. 1, 2. <hi>They that truſt in the Lord, ſhall be as Mount Zion, which cannot be removed, but abideth for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jer. 31.3.—<hi>I have loved thee with an everlaſting love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>John 10.28, 29. <hi>I give unto them everlaſting life, and they ſhall never periſh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>What can be ſpoken more plainly?</p>
               <p>Jer. 32.4. <hi>I will make an everlaſting Covenant with them, and I will put my fear into their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All which are ſo plain and full, as ſhould put an end to all altercations and ſilence all Diſputes in this Point. We may conclude, nothing can change or alter the <hi>foundation of God:</hi> none can reverſe the Seal of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, nor break one link of that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153887:21"/>golden Chain. The Creature, as it had no influence upon <hi>the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> ſo neither hath it any power to alter it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Hereticks nor wicked Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers cannot. It is the plain Doctrine of our Apoſtle here; his only aim be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to comfort the Church againſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers and men ſeduced; neither one or the other were laid in <hi>the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Not <hi>the gates of Hell;</hi> Matth. 16.18, <hi>i. e.</hi> all the power and policy of Hell combined; all the wiles of the Devil cannot conquer one Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier in Chriſts Camp, much leſs ſhall rout the whole Army.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Not the Will of man it ſelf; becauſe God by infallible grace, ceaſes not to govern and diſpoſe the acts of the Will in them he hath known and called. As an inferiour Orb cannot alter the motion of the firſt Sphere, becauſe it is moved with and by it; no more can the Will of man alter <hi>the foundation of God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153887:21"/>the acts thereof are guided by and diſpoſed according to Gods Will and fore-knowledg in the <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, The <hi>gates of Hell</hi> are ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the <hi>will</hi> of man, they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>it,</hi> when it had moſt ſtrength and freedom in Paradiſe; therefore if <hi>the gates of Hell,</hi> which are ſtronger, cannot alter nor prevail againſt the <hi>foundation,</hi> the <hi>will</hi> of man which is weaker and depends thereon, cannot do it. Satan by his inſtruments, <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menaeus, Philetus, Pelagians, Jeſuits and Arminians,</hi> with other ſecret Enemies to God and a Divine Life; may and do deſtroy the <hi>temporary</hi> faith of ſuch as were left out of <hi>the foundation,</hi> but can never deſtroy the <hi>juſtifying</hi> faith of ſuch, as were then taken, known and marked out to be the Lords.</p>
               <p>But the Doctrine conſiſts of two parts; we will ſever them a while, to joyn them together more firmly: as the breaking of a bone, doth final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occaſion it to become ſtronger in its Union.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:153887:22"/>
               <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> part concerns the <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> which is the Purpoſe and Will of God, whereby he eternally deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to create and diſpoſe of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men, to their ſeveral Ends, by certain means. Not all to one end; the <hi>Creatures end,</hi> is according to the <hi>Creators Love;</hi> his <hi>Love</hi> was not alike to all (diverſity of gifts and ſervices ſheweth it), being tied to none. Juſtice and Mercy both, as well as Knowledg, Power and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, took place in laying <hi>the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> that God might be glorified in both.</p>
               <p>This is expreſt by our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.40. <hi>Two ſhall be in the field, the one is taken, the other left.</hi> There is two of a Tribe and one of a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14. As it is and ſhall be in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Decree, ſo it was in the <hi>foundation.</hi> Two determined to be created, Angels and Men; both fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the one is taken, the other left. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Deus non expectabat Angelos,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153887:22"/>ſed proecipitavit,</hi> as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it; the Angel was left without mercy, for a prey of puniſhment, that elder off-ſpring of Divine Love was expell'd from the beatifick Preſence, the Imperial Robe of Heaven was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended upon Man, who lay on a Dunghil, <hi>he</hi> was drawn out, waſh'd, gilded over with grace, the true ſeed of Glory. Two Brothers in one Womb, before they had done either good or evil; the Decree was paſt on them, the <hi>foundation</hi> laid, that the one ſhould be loved, the other hated, <hi>i. e.</hi> paſt over. Two Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> both ſin greatly, little difference in the act, both betray him, but God puts a difference in the event, the one repents being elected, the other deſpairs, being paſt by in <hi>the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and ſo ordained to perdition. So the renowned <hi>Auguſtin</hi> againſt <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Pelagian;</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">In one and the ſame Decree of Diſpoſition, ſaith he, one is rejected by Juſtice, not Chance, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther elected by Mercy and not Merit:</q>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:153887:23"/>by mercy in the Elector, without any merit or act of Faith or Free-will done or fore-ſeen to be done, in the Perſon elected. Some are choſen to believe to build up their own and the faith of others: ſome others, left deſtitute of Gods ſaving and aſſiſting grace, do err concerning the Faith, deſtroy both their own and the ſeeming faith of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. God making thus of the ſame Lump, one Veſſel <hi>to honour,</hi> another to <hi>diſhonour,</hi> without injuſtice or reſpect to perſons. <hi>Is there unrighteouſneſs with God? He hath mercy on whom he will have mercy and whom he will he hardneth.</hi> Good things in good Men being effects of Gods mercy, and comments upon Election; when as Evil things in Evil men, are but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents of <hi>preterition.</hi> The neceſſity then of every man attaining his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained End, comes not from the power of mans Will, freely diſpoſing it ſelf to this or that Object, only through moral perſuaſion, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 9.16.), but from the Will and Power
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153887:23"/>of God, laying a ſure <hi>foundation</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his <hi>fore-knowledg.</hi> Acts 2. laſt Ver. <hi>He added daily to the Church ſuch as ſhould be ſaved.</hi> Obſerve the phraſe; <hi>Such as ſhould,</hi> having refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>foundation of God.</hi> Not ſuch as <hi>would,</hi> till of <hi>unwilling,</hi> they were made <hi>willing.</hi> But more fully, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. <hi>As many as were ordained to eternal life believed.</hi> There was then an Ordination in <hi>the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> before any actual apprehenſion of Chriſt by Faith, or poſſibility thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.15. It is ſaid of <hi>Paul, He is a choſen Veſſel unto me.</hi> John 17.12. <hi>Judas</hi> is called <hi>the child of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> i. e. ordained to perdition, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> explains it. Theſe things we read done in time, but we know they were ordained to be done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time. There was a <hi>foundation</hi> laid, as of <hi>Creation,</hi> ſo of <hi>diſpoſition</hi> of all things created to their ſeveral ends by means.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:153887:24"/>
               <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> part, concerning the <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of</hi> it. It remains <hi>ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> In regard of the Decree it ſelf, which doth ſo knit together, the Cauſe, the Means and the End: that the known of the Lord, engraff'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the body of Chriſt, by the grace of <hi>Election,</hi> are ſure to remain to the end, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.25. — <hi>It fell not, becauſe it was founded upon a Rock.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.5. <hi>They are kept by the power of God, through faith unto ſalvation.</hi> 1 John 3.9. — <hi>His ſeed remaineth in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This may be further confirmed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> from the <hi>immutability</hi> of an abſolute Purpoſe in God: in him is <hi>no ſhadow of change.</hi> Rom. 8.29. <hi>Whom he did fore-know, he alſo did predeſtinate to be conformed to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of his Son,</hi> &amp;c. Cap. 9.11. <hi>That the purpoſe of God might ſtand, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Election,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> From the Prayer of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 17.15. in <hi>Peter</hi> for all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <hi>I have prayed for thee, that thy
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153887:24"/>faith fail not.</hi> And we are ſure, that Chriſt was heard in <hi>that he prayed for.</hi> There was ever a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and agreement between his and the Fathers Will: and this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatory Prayer, doth in ſome ſenſe continue. <hi>He ever liveth to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for us.</hi> Beſides a Promiſe he left us, that whatſoever we did ask the <hi>Father in his Name,</hi> it ſhould be granted. We ask with ſighs and groans, knowing our own weakneſs, for the grace of perſeverance. Nay, he taught us to ask it, in every Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of his own Prayer, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it. Therefore we may be <hi>ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> From the nature of <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy;</hi> which is a falling away from Faith <hi>hiſtorical,</hi> attended refined Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, whereby <hi>Wolves</hi> may be in the Church for a time, undiſcerned. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19. <hi>They went out from us, becauſe they were not of us,</hi> but only in ſhew and outward appearance, they were but Meteors, not fixed Stars, Pictures, not living Men in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153887:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> From a main abſurdity following the contrary. If any one ſtone could be moved in this <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> any of Gods Elect periſh by falling totally and finally from the grace of Faith, then all might, there being the ſame reaſon for the falling of all, as for one. Chriſt and his Members make up but one Body, one Chriſt: and is it poſſible a part of Chriſt ſhould be found burning in Hell? Can the myſtical Body of Chriſt be diſſolved? If the former be true, ſo muſt the latter, and the death of Chriſt be of none effect, and all the Promiſes of Grace come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Which is horrible to conceive, and impoſſible to be done.</p>
               <p>Renowned <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> ſpeaking of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaith, that he had a Power given <hi>Non peccare ſi vellet,</hi> not to ſin if he would; to ſtand if he would; not a Power to will what he might and ſhould; but to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> he gives both Power and Will; they partake of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153887:25"/>Grace, <hi>quâ efficitur ut Velint.</hi> Hath not Chriſt ſaid it, our faith and fruit ſhall <hi>remain?</hi> This hath wrought with ſome Papiſts,
<note place="margin">Lumbard, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas, Greg. de Valan.</note> that they have been conſtrained to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that Faith work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Love, is a conſtant Habit in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of it ſelf and the <hi>Author</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing and preſerving it; and that there is a poſſibility of loſing it, only in reſpect of the frailty of the <hi>Subject</hi> wherein it is.</p>
               <p>Some ſay, the Elect of God, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and regenerate, may and do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch ſins as deſerve the total cutting off and the final loſing of Grace; but that they riſe again by true Repentance and are not finally caſt away, it is the work of God; who by his Power preſerves them, as he laid them in the <hi>foundation.</hi> Pſal. 37.24. <hi>The ſteps of a good man are order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lord; though he fall, he ſhall not utterly be caſt down, the Lord upholds him with his hand.</hi> O bleſſed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153887:26"/>be God! Juſt men may fall from the <hi>inherent</hi> righteouſneſs of <hi>ſanctification,</hi> by ſome great ſin, and ſo bring tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral judgments, yea, death upon themſelves; as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.24. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30. it is manifeſted: yet never fall from the <hi>imputed</hi> righteouſneſs of <hi>Juſtification:</hi> the <hi>foundation</hi> is ſure on Gods ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>foundation ſtandeth ſure,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Subject.</hi> The known of the Lord, engraft into Chriſt, by the grace of <hi>Election,</hi> may be, are or ſhall be made ſure of Salvation. This certainty they gather divers ways, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. By the teſtimony of the Spirit; <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.16. <hi>The Spirit it ſelf beareth witneſs with our ſpirit that we are the children of God.</hi> Only here men muſt be careful to diſtinguiſh the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the Spirit of God, from the ſubtil illuſions of Satan and the deceitful motions of their own hearts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By the manifeſt effects of Gods Love towards us, in us. For upon all his Elect, living till they be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153887:26"/>of them, he beſtows theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing gifts in ſome meaſure; namely</p>
               <p>Firſt, A living Faith to believe in, caſt themſelves upon and lay hold on Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 6.29. <hi>This is the work of God, that ye believe on him, whom he hath ſent.</hi> Epheſ. 2.8. Faith is the Work of God and his gift.</p>
               <p>To which it may be replyed, by a <hi>Pelagian, Jeſuit</hi> or <hi>Arminian;</hi> that a man may believe by the power of his own <hi>will,</hi> aſſenting to a moral perſuaſion, without the efficiency of ſupernatural Power; and therefore the encreaſe only of Faith is the gift and work of God, the beginning from Nature and Free-will.</p>
               <p>But doth not this make the Law of Nature ſwell to ſo high a tide as Grace? advance man with God, and bring the dribling River to vye with the drowning Ocean? By this Rule, man muſt do the hardeſt work him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and leave the eaſier for God and his Grace. He that can raiſe himſelf from death to life; is much more able to continue himſelf in life.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:153887:27"/>
               <p>Of this Opinion was <hi>Auguſtin</hi> once, <hi>viz. that faith was in us and from us primarily:</hi> but by reading <hi>Cyprian</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe words of <hi>Paul, What haſt thou O man that thou haſt not received?</hi> renounced his Errour, proving plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that not only the encreaſe, but the beginning of Faith were the gift of God, or elſe we might ſay, we had ſomething we did not receive.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Love. Faith firſt works Love and then works by Love; as the Workman ſets an edge on his Tools, and then cuts and carves with them. And therefore for the moſt part, they are in Scripture joyn'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. No Love, no Faith. And Love advances by equal paces with Faith; as the heat of the day advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with the ſhining of the Sun.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The power of Prayer and Supplication, with zeal and fervency. No ſooner was <hi>Paul</hi> converted, but the next word is, <hi>Behold he prayeth!</hi> Heb. 9.11. It is reported of <hi>Luther,</hi> that when he prayed, it was with ſo
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153887:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>much reverence, as if he were pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, and with ſo much bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as if he had been ſpeaking with his Friend. Gods Spirit tunes the ſtrings of the affections and then they ſhall make ſweet melody in Prayer. The ſymbols of the Spirit were <hi>fiery Tongues,</hi> and a <hi>mighty ruſhing Wind;</hi> and where-ever the Spirit is, there will be Prayer <hi>in the Spirit.</hi> Where life is, there will be breath. God never had, nor ever will have a ſtill-born Child.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Perſeverance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in all theſe with reſolution and purpoſe of heart, to rely upon Chriſt, call upon his Name, Love his People, what ever befall them, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.6. <hi>We are confident of this very thing, that he which hath begun a good work in you, will perform it, unto the day of Chriſt.</hi> That in the end we may ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.7. <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe,</hi> &amp;c. Rom. 8.38, 39. <hi>If God be for us, who can be againſt us. I am
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153887:28"/>perſuaded, that neither life nor death, principalities nor powers, things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent nor things to come, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus!</hi> Therefore the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God ſtands <hi>ſure,</hi> both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of God and Man.</p>
               <p>A Doctrine naturally flowing from the Text and meaning of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: ſo expounded by the beſt Learned in every Age, who have by their Writings illuſtrated the truth of the Goſpel, confirmed in Scripture plainly, and by the works of good men, ſince the <hi>Pelagian</hi> Hereſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to diſturb the Church.</p>
               <p>I may conclude it, as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> doth his ſpeech to the <hi>Jews,</hi> Act. 5.38, 39. if the foundation of our ſalvation were of or in <hi>man,</hi> it might and would certainly come to nought; but being in and from God, it cannot be <hi>deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> all ſuch as may endeavour it, ſhall be found fighters againſt God.</p>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:153887:28"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I.</head>
                  <p>In the application of this Point, we find matter of inſtructive <hi>information</hi> divers ways, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> To point out unto us the true ſubject of <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi> men paſt over by God and left out of the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi> Every <hi>plant my heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath not planted, ſhall be rooted out.</hi> Such and only ſuch are ſubject to Apoſtacy, the reſt are preſerved, by the <hi>power of God unto ſalvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> It ſhews us the danger of falſe Opinions, to fret like a <hi>Canker,</hi> to diſturb, deſtroy, eat into the body of Church and State; one infecting another, <hi>Arius</hi> his Hereſie was at firſt but a little ſpark, yet how did it ſpread and fire the whole World; what woful waſte was made of many flouriſhing Congregations &amp; Churches, when the Orthodox Biſhops were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iled and their flocks ſcattered? when the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> by their ſeparation made
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153887:29"/>a diviſion in the <hi>African</hi> Churches, what violences and outrages were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed againſt faithful Chriſtians, both Paſtors and People? And in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, when the <hi>German</hi> Anabaptiſts ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated themſelves from the other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches what woful work did they make? how much did they obſtruct and even hazard the work of Reformation begun ſo happily by <hi>Luther,</hi> and ſucceſsfully carried on for ſome years together? And thus with grief we live to ſee <hi>Popery and Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm</hi> to do the like miſchief in our days. Men ſhould be afraid to raiſe ſuch Opinions, to bring ſuch Owls, amidſt the glorious light of Truth, that hath ſhined ſo ſplendidly in our Horizon; and be aſhamed to receive them, being raiſed. Authority ſhould be carefully vigilant, to ſuppreſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, to oppoſe all thoſe who ſeek <hi>craftily</hi> to undermine <hi>the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God;</hi> that they may be cured or cut off.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:153887:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Hence we learn, that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks are never able to ſeduce the Elect; however they may entromb themſelves in the ruins of that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity which they once profeſſed. <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menaeus and Philetus</hi> deſtroy the faith of ſome, <hi>nevertheleſs,</hi> the <hi>foundation of God ſtands ſure.</hi> God will have a Church for ever. See the anſwer of God, when the Prophet complain'd, there was none left but he: <hi>I have left unto my ſelf ſeven thouſand, which never bowed the knee to Baal.</hi> This conſtancy of all thoſe fair and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Souls, who have in all Ages been ſetled in the Truth, like Pillars of Diamonds, not ſhaken with the Counterbufs of damnable Errour, took not riſe from themſelves. <hi>Noah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Peter,</hi> left to themſelves, to ſtand on their own bottom, fall ſtrangely and wofully, and make known to a world of Ages, that they are but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fleſh: and the beſt of men living, if left to themſelves but one moment, would deſtroy themſelves in that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153887:30"/>they are but like glaſſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a bottom, which break as ſoon ae they are out of hand. If they continue to ſhine, it is not by their own luſtre, but by borrowed beams of the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> and the light remains no longer than the Sun ſhines. The faireſt Flowers of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe would wither, if not watered with drops from Heaven. How have the <hi>mighty</hi> fallen, when the <hi>Almighty</hi> hath not ſtood by them. All their ability proceeds from the Love of God in <hi>the foundation,,</hi> and the power of his grace, ſtirring them to renew their repentance. Neither is there any ground here laid for <hi>preſumption,</hi> that a man ſhould grow careleſs and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, becauſe of what God hath done; no: Grace never relaxeth the ſinews of obedience in the leaſt degree. It is perfectly innocent of that abuſe. The Poiſon is not in the Roſe, but in the Spider. Beſides, there are ſigns of <hi>Election</hi> after deſcribed, which if they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153887:30"/>cannot be found in perſons, they cannot be aſſured of any portion in the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi> That man who daringly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes, ſaying, Let me live as I liſt, <hi>the foundation of God ſtands ſure,</hi> and ſo gives way to his unſwayed fancy, and makes this a pillow for his ſloath and caſteth off all care for the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of his Soul; I will not ſay he was rejected in <hi>the foundation;</hi> but this I dare affirm, he never yet felt the burden of ſin, nor the comfort of grace; and except he change his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and behaviour, he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver receive benefit by it. At once, men were laid in <hi>the foundation</hi> and ordained <hi>to work out their ſalvation with fear and trembling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Hence we learn the duty of Learned Men, with all in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, called to publiſh and defend the truth of Chriſt, ſeaſonably, boldly, yet diſcreetly to ſtand and contend againſt the enemies thereof, Politick ſilence in this caſe, is a branch of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> againſt the King of his Church.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153887:31"/>Not to defend the Truth is to betray it. When there are many oppoſits, the friends of Chriſt muſt eſpecially ſtand up with courage and reſolution. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt counter-work the Devil. There ſhould be a kind of <hi>Antiperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis</hi> in the ſouls of true Believers, as in the fire, that burns hotteſt, when the air round about it, is coldeſt. The middle Region is therefore cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, becauſe the greateſt heat of each, taketh the reflection from the lower and upper heat above; ſuch an <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſtaſis</hi> ſhould be found in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; they ſhould be hotteſt in the coldeſt times, their hearts ſhould be fulleſt of activity for Chriſt, in times of greateſt oppoſition againſt him. Our ſervice at ſuch a time is moſt acceptable and uſeful. Memorable is the courage of <hi>Luther,</hi> who obtain'd through Chriſt a vigour of ſpirit which never bowed under the evils that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſted him; being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to <hi>Worms,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Malch. Adam. Vit. Luth.</note> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded from going, by
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153887:31"/>reaſon of the fury he might meet with there, and the multitude of Enemies; replied, <q rend="inline">If I knew there were as many Devils as there are Tiles up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Houſes, yet thither I would go.</q> Thus our Apoſtle here, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dems the Errour and names the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; it cannot be unlawful to call them <hi>Papiſts and Arminians,</hi> who maintain the Errours of both. The like teſtimony was given by our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Worthies</hi> in the Reign of Qu. <hi>Mary,</hi> not only in white and black, but red too; by which they came to ſhine and glitter at ſuch a rate, as hath obtain'd them a Reputation, which will have a glorious mention, ſo long as there be Stars above and Ages below. So it ſhould be now: the thoughts of their flames, ſhould kindle zeal in us. Chriſt is many ways oppoſed this day, and we ſhould earneſtly contend for Chriſt. Now there are many tempters, and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and revilers, therefore now Chriſt ſhould have many <hi>Champions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:153887:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II.</head>
                  <p>Secondly, This Doctrine doth moſt directly ſerve to confute the antient <hi>Pelagians,</hi> in this and other parts of the World; as labouring to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw this <hi>foundation of God,</hi> and to lay another upon the frail, uncertain power of mans Will; in their <hi>doctrine,</hi> preferring Nature to and above Grace, as the <hi>Pelagians</hi> did; maintaining partly, a total fall from Chriſt, as ſome <hi>Lutherans</hi> do; and partly a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and final fall, as <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians;</hi> who make Chriſtians a meer ball of Fortune, to be toſſed up and down at their pleaſure; repreſenting <hi>Grace</hi> as voluble and uncertain as the Heathen did <hi>Fortunes. Grace</hi> with them is but a thing of Glaſs, which while it ſhines, is broken: with them the <hi>Veſſels of Glory,</hi> are little better than <hi>crazy</hi> Veſſels, which may be daſht in pieces like <hi>a Potters Veſſel.</hi> They can remove them from Heaven to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153887:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>Hell, as often as they pleaſe. With a daring Pen, they can blot Names out of the <hi>book of Life;</hi> and with as much eaſe, reverſe the <hi>Seal</hi> of Heaven when they liſt. They tell us, there is no ſuch certainty in <hi>the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> no ſuch abſolute Knowledg, no ſuch impoſſibility in regard of God; of falling off from Chriſt, of return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again to the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> to the bondage of <hi>Egypt,</hi> of feeding upon the Milk and Honey of the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> againſt the plain Words and meaning of our Apoſtle in this place. So that St. <hi>Auguſtins</hi> Title, <hi>viz. The Hatchet of Hereticks,</hi> may not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly applied to it. It is the Axe of <hi>Arminians,</hi> cutting down their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, <hi>that the elect of God after effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual calling, may fall away finally.</hi> Whoſe aſſertion, like another <hi>Goliah</hi> fighting againſt the living God, is ſo unſound, ſo uncomfortable, ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently againſt the Divine Word, the works of the beſt Men, who were the Lights of their time, the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153887:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Holy Ghoſt, in all Ages, that every <hi>David</hi> may and will fling a ſtone at it, crying as of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Down with it, even to the ground and lower! For the Lord knows who are his; the <hi>foundation of God ſtands ſure,</hi> and the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> III.</head>
                  <p>Thirdly, Here is matter of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar comfort and eſtabliſhment to all true Believers; and that,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Againſt all Hereticks, Errours and the falling away of Eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for Gifts and Place, men of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal note in the Church; <hi>they were not of us,</hi> though they diſſembled a long time; they were not Sons, elſe they had remained in the Houſe for ever. Many follow <hi>Religion</hi> as the Hounds do the game, only for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; they reſpect the Truth not for ſingle but ſiniſter ends: Chriſt is not ſweet to them for <hi>himſelf,</hi> but only for his Rings and Jewels. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153887:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>in <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> and no wonder if they end in <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi> Trees that are unſound at the roots, ſoon ceaſe from putting forth of fruits; and they who are for the preſent corrupt, will for the future be openly prophane. Let none be offended at ſuch, nor ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd at the profeſſion of <hi>Religion;</hi> the ſheep doth not deſpiſe its fleece, becauſe the Wolf hath worn it, neither do any blame a Cryſtal River, becauſe ſome melancholly perſons have drown'd themſelves in it. The beſt drugs have their adulterate. And as long as there are true Pearls, there will be counterfeit, Though there have been falſe colours, yet diſeſteem not thoſe that are dyed in <hi>grain,</hi> for ſuch there are. Be not as bad Husbands, who having a ſpot on their Coat, cut off the whole Cloath, when they ſhould only waſh off the dirt. You make a good profeſſion, be ſure to make your profeſſion good. Sincerity is the baſis of perpetuity.</p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:153887:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Againſt Perſecution, verbal or real. Things that are exceeding ſharp, call for Sugar to ſweeten them. Troubles in the fleſh, have a moſt ungrateful taſte for the Creatures pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; now this truth is as Sugar to make them ſweet, that they may down the better. Gods Elect may be oppreſſed, ſupppreſſed they cannot be. <hi>They are kept by the power of God</hi> againſt all oppoſition. Their blood ſhall be as ſeed; by the death of one, many will revive. Dogs that have no teeth may bark, but cannot bite. Serpents that have no ſtings may hiſs, but cannot hurt. Believers like the Moon, ſhall wade out of their ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, by keeping a conſtant motion. <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> ſhall paſs away, but <hi>the foundation of God ſtandeth ſure.</hi> O ye Saints of God! in the midſt of your dangers, have an Eye to your ſecurity. Providence hath a beautiful face, even when it puts on its black mask. God hath fair ends in his fouleſt ways. If the Earth be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153887:34"/>dirty under your feet, know for your comfort, the Heavens are not cloudy over your heads. Who ever frown, God ſmiles. Suck from this breaſt of Conſolation. Fetch you Honey out of the Lions belly. Let this prove a Cordial to ſupport you in all your fainting fits.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Againſt worldly proſperity of wicked men, though they be in a flouriſhing condition, vex the ſouls of the righteous, and deride their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; a day is coming, when they ſhall be trodden under feet. The Sun of outward ſplendour caſteth its rays upon them, only to warm their heads againſt a ſtorm. The ſame hand that poureth out mercies on them like Oil, will pour down his wrath upon them like water. Under all their proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous gallantry, their hearts are ſinful, and in the midſt of all their wealth, their eſtates are doleful. O, know, it is better going to <hi>Zion</hi> through the Valley of <hi>Baca,</hi> than to pitch your tents in the Plains of <hi>Sodom.</hi> The
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153887:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtalled Ox would not ſet ſo high a rate on his Paſture, did he know, it was only to fit him for the Butcher. It is their proſperity; but as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaid, <hi>Abſit a nobis, Chariſſimi, talis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitas!</hi> From ſuch proſperity, good Lord, deliver us! Great and Rich Men will not know you, take no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of you but for their own ends, yet the Lord knoweth you and <hi>the foundation ſtands ſure,</hi> which wicked men, when they have done their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, cannot overthrow.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Againſt their own ſinful failings, weakneſſes and infirmities, to which they are unwillingly and with ſorrow ſubject: (ſo it will be whileſt they are cloathed in robes of Clay; as the Mortar wherein Garlick hath been ſtamp'd, will alway ſmell of it, ſo your beſt actions will favour ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the old man:) Yet if <hi>the foundation</hi> of God ſtandeth ſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all things, then againſt ſin. <hi>Sin,</hi> cannot quench that Divine flame of Love. The Church had her <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:153887:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>her infirmities, her ſleepy fits, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. Though blacked and ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied, yet is the Dove ſtill. Chriſt could ſee her faith and wink at her failings. He who drew <hi>Alexanders</hi>'s Picture whileſt there was a ſcar on his Face, drew him with his Finger on his ſcar. Chriſt puts the Finger of mercy upon the ſcars of his Saints. He will not throw away his Pearls, for every ſpeck of dirt. The Roſe is a fragrant Flower, though it be ſurrounded with prickles. The Paſs-over was a Feaſt, though eaten with bitter herbs; and though a ſingle ſtring in playing of a Leſſon may jar; yet the main may be muſical. God doth not as men do: we often take notice of the Evil is in others, and over-look the good; our Eye is on the flaw in the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, when we obſerve not its ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: but God takes notice of the good in his People and from that he denominates them, and for that he receives them. And as ſin cannot, ſo neither can men commit ſuch ſins, as
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:153887:36"/>are able to change or overthrow this <hi>foundation.</hi> Regenerate men will not; the habit of Grace ſo orders and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſeth of their Will, that they never ſin with full conſent, delight and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, as natural men do; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when Sathan aſſaults us with our ſins, we muſt run unto <hi>the foundation of God,</hi> and the means appointed for our Redemption and Salvation.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>But in what eſtate is a Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man, falling into ſome grievous ſin?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> He is in a dangerous eſtate; it may be no Errour to ſay <hi>damnable,</hi> in reſpect of himſelf and his own act. Grievous ſins do ſubject the beſt men, meritoriouſly, to the condemnation of the Law, and to the forfeiture of all that right which they had of the pardon of former ſins by vertue of the Covenant: and that theſe do not <hi>de facto</hi> condemn the Believer, is to be aſcribed to the grace of <hi>Election</hi> in the <hi>foundation;</hi> and in that regard we ſay and truly, that the Spirit of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153887:36"/>Regeneration leaves not his reſidence in ſuch a Perſon, but only ſuſpends his working for a time: Grace is not extinguiſhed but oppreſt; it lies like the Phoenix in her aſhes, till God in his appointed time ſhall mercifully look again upon him, by the powerful beams of his Spirit ſcattering thoſe miſts which darken and hinder the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſhining forth of his illuſtrious Creature. <hi>Grace:</hi> as it did in <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>David</hi> (than whoſe Names, the Tongues of Men can hardly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce any thing more pleaſing.) <hi>I am the Lord, I change not, therefore ye ſons of</hi> Jacob <hi>are not conſumed. My grace is ſufficient</hi> to revive; cleanſe and ſuſtein all thoſe whom I have ſealed. How are we bound to God for his free Love? chuſing us, ſetting his <hi>Seal</hi> upon us, that we might be known for his in all Places and Aſſemblies; and that none might ever lay claim unto us. <hi>If God be for us, who can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:153887:37"/>
                  <p>Object. <hi>But if the foundation be ſo ſure, to what end is that Exhortation,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.10. <hi>Give all diligence to make your calling and election ſure? It ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth here, that the certainty of Gods Decree dependeth on mans will.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is a two-fold certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; 1. Of <hi>determination</hi> in Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and decree; and ſo, we are not to conceive that the Exhortation is propounded with reference to God, or that which he hath done, as though our endeavour were wanting to make it ſure, or as if we could add perfection to his action, which we can no more do, than add bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Sun.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of <hi>apprehenſion</hi> and perſuaſion as to our ſelves and others, expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by degrees fears and doubts; by an holy life we muſt be aſſured, and aſſure others, of our effectual Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; ſo that we (and others ſeeing <hi>our good works</hi>) may be aſſured of our election to eternal life.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:153887:37"/>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>The foundation is ſure, but is the building thereon as ſure?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Men may <hi>lay</hi> a ſure founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet make a ruinous building. God cannot. Where there is the ſame matter, Skill, Power and Will, there the <hi>foundation</hi> and <hi>building</hi> muſt be of equal force and ſureneſs; and ſo it is in this <hi>foundation.</hi> Not, but that the Houſe built on a Rock may be daſh'd with Waves; though the Seal of God be of an eternal Efficacy; yet the impreſſion thereof may be ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, that it may not be ſo fairly viſible to the Eye; though the Root and ſeed of Grace cannot be loſt, this excludes not, but that the flouriſh and fragancy thereof may be loſt; and though the eminency and beauty of it may be loſt, yet <hi>the foundation is ſure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We are now to proceed unto the <hi>ſecond</hi> branch of the Text, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Signs and <hi>marks</hi> of <hi>Election,</hi> whereby men may know whether
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153887:38"/>they were laid in the <hi>foundation;</hi> and it runs thus:</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Let every one that nameth the name of Chriſt, depart from iniquity.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>This is the other part of the <hi>Seal</hi> concerning the <hi>foundation;</hi> the <hi>Seal</hi> of God in <hi>Man;</hi> and it is two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Naming the name of Chriſt;</hi> being <hi>called</hi> after his Name, <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Which is either done <hi>vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually,</hi> as in the believing <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> before Chriſt, or <hi>actually,</hi> in Believers after Chriſt: ſo his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were firſt called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch.</hi> Or elſe, <hi>calling</hi> upon his <hi>Name;</hi> which doth neceſſarily follow: ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the duty of Chriſtians, to call upon the name of Chriſt. Both theſe together, are certain ſigns of <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>Departing from iniquity.</hi> If this purpoſe be in us, joyned with an anſwerable practice, we may be aſſured of Election.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:153887:38"/>
                  <p>Some there have been and are, who depart from ſin, without <hi>naming the name of Chriſt,</hi> or believing in him; as the Heathen Philoſophers, <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> who attain'd to a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty moral and vertuous deportment; which in St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> judgment could be no other, than inferiour Workings of the Divine Spirit, ſome dimmer and cooler Rays of <hi>the Sun of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> as he is the light which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightneth every one that cometh into the World.</p>
                  <p>Others again there are, who have <hi>name</hi> enough, glory in the name of Chriſtians, but will depart from no iniquity; a name they have, as the Angel of the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> had, but nothing elſe, and may be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fitly to <hi>Sodoms</hi> trees and fruits, which as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, are trees and no trees, fruit and no fruit,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chryſoſt. Hom.</hi> 8. <hi>in</hi> 1. <hi>ad Theſ.</hi>
                     </note> all in ſhew and nothing in ſubſtance: or to painted fire which hath no heat, only
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153887:39"/>the reſemblance of fire; and to weeds in the Corn-field, which look like flowers in the Garden, yet are not flowers; but what will the name, the appearance profit, where the thing is wanting? God hath joyn'd theſe in his Seal, <hi>naming</hi> and <hi>departing,</hi> as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of <hi>Election,</hi> let none put them aſunder in their lives and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations; but labour really to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſo much of Chriſt, as may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare him to be <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſubſtantial Chriſtians; that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Grace is not a vain Notion, but a real, vital, energetical Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; for ſo it is and will appear to be where-ever it is.</p>
                  <p>Men may name the name of Chriſt three ways:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Inwardly</hi> only; in the heart: as <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> did, believing in Chriſt, not profeſſing for fear of the <hi>Jews.</hi> Which was the blot of the latter of the two; he was a Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bird.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Outwardly</hi> only; profeſſing not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153887:39"/>believing; as all Formaliſts, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, temporizers do. Such a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and amazing Majeſty there is in goodneſs, that all deſire to wear her Livery, though few care to perform her ſervice. Like proud Courtiers, who would willingly be Favourites, but ſcorn to attend. Theſe, like ſome kind of Nuts, are all ſhell and no kernel; all body without a Soul, or as falſe Looking-glaſſes, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent thoſe faces which are not in them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Both ways, <hi>inwardly</hi> and <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly,</hi> believing and profeſſing. Faith and Zeal, make a compleat Chriſtian. No <hi>zeal,</hi> no <hi>faith,</hi> no profeſſion, no apprehenſion of Chriſt ordinarily. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward faith, without outward profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, cannot be, is not ſufficient to ſalvation. Faith juſtifieth our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but profeſſion juſtifieth our faith. A dumb faith is not a <hi>Divine,</hi> but the <hi>faith of Devils.</hi> Joh. 12.42, 43. <hi>Among the chief Rulers alſo many believed on him, and becauſe of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153887:40"/>Phariſees they did not confeſs him, leſt they ſhould be put out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue; for they loved the praiſe of men more than the praiſe of God.</hi> The light of Religion, muſt not be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in a Dark-Lanthorn, to be ſhewn when our Intereſt will permit and to hide it at other times. Among the <hi>Romans</hi> there was a Law, that every man ſhould wear a badg of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Trade, whereby he might be known. Thus doth Chriſt require of all his Servants. Confeſſion of the mouth, without faith in the Heart, is groſs <hi>hypocriſie;</hi> and to pretend Faith without Confeſſion with the mouth, is but Hypocriſie and Cowardize.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in his Confeſſions hath a notable ſtory of one <hi>Victorinus,</hi> who was in his old Age converted to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; and came to <hi>Simplicianus</hi> (one at that time eminent for Piety) whiſpering ſoftly in his Ears, theſe words, <hi>Sum Chriſtianus,</hi> I am a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; but this holy man anſwered,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153887:40"/>
                     <hi>Non credo, nec deputabo te inter Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianos, niſi in Eccleſia Chriſti te vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro;</hi> i. e. I do not believe it, neither ſhall I reckon <hi>thee amongſt the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſtians, unleſs I ſee thee in the publick Aſſemblies of Chriſtians.</hi> God requires the Religion of the heart and alſo of the mouth. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. The Pope indeed, ſaith to his Vaſſals, <hi>my ſon give me thy heart;</hi> be a Papiſt in heart, and then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, do what you will; and the <hi>Swenkfeldians</hi> of old took away all external ſervice: the <hi>Libertines</hi> of later times ſay, That it is ſufficient to ſerve God with the hidden man of the heart: But God requires to be glorified with our Spirits and our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; both are his. He will have the Jewel with its Cabinet. This is that our Saviour means, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.32, 33. <hi>If we confeſs him before men, he will confeſs us before the Father which is in Heaven.</hi> So the Apoſtle, as before, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. <hi>With the heart man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves unto righteouſneſs, and with the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153887:41"/>mouth confeſſion is made unto ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Whence it may be probably ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, that <hi>Eliſha.</hi> (2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.) did not approve of <hi>Naamans</hi> reſolution, ſaying, that he believed only in <hi>the God of Iſrael,</hi> yet went away with a purpoſe to bow down in the houſe of <hi>Rimmon;</hi> nor gave him any warrant ſo to do: If ſuch politick pretences were currant, men might be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans without fear or danger; thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of brave, generous Men and Women, had loſt their bloud in vain. If <hi>diſſimulation</hi> might paſs for Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, all People might go to Heaven without martyrdom.</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe once again, men ſay, they believe in Chriſt, be baptized, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtians, partake of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, joyn with the ſolemn Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and yet ſeem outwardly for the fear, love or praiſe of men, to profeſs or allow of Idolatrous ſervice, Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions ſtriking at the <hi>foundation of God,</hi> omiſſions of good Duties, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of great ſins, for profit, of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153887:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>profaneneſs of life for carnal delight, leſt they ſhould be perſecuted or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called; like the old <hi>Priſcillianiſts,</hi> whoſe main deſign was to ſave a whole skin, they made little rekon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Profeſſion and thought they might ſay and unſay, ſwear and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear, ſo but in their hearts, they did cleave unto the truth. Hear <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines</hi> ſentence of theſe Perſons;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bellar. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Eccleſ. milit.</hi> c. 13. <hi>ad finem.</hi>
                     </note> thoſe which do not confeſs the Faith, but retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in their heart, make outward profeſſion of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, are not good men, neither can they be ſaved.</p>
                  <p>To explain this a little further, know, men may profeſs or allow of evil divers ways; <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. By <hi>Authority,</hi> commanding, provoking, or tolerating evil. As <hi>Saul</hi> did by enjoyning <hi>Doeg,</hi> a villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Butcher, to kill the Lords Prieſts; and <hi>Ahaz,</hi> who ſent a pattern of the <hi>Altar at Damaſcus</hi> to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153887:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>Prieſt, enjoyning him to build ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to it, and offer upon it. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 16.10. And ſo did <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian</hi> the Tyrant, who gave the People leave to kill the Chriſtians, where ever they met them. That evil which is committed by our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation, is ours by juſt imputation. Our Lord is ſaid to be crucified at <hi>Rome,</hi> (<hi>Revel.</hi> 11.8.) becauſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced by a <hi>Roman</hi> Judg, executed by <hi>Roman</hi> Soldiers and put to death by the Authority of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire: yet the death of Chriſt, all along the Scriptures, is charged upon the <hi>Jews,</hi> becauſe though the execution of it was by the <hi>Romans,</hi> yet the provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation was from the <hi>Jews.</hi> Acts 2.23. Again, the Kings of the Earth are taxed, (<hi>Revel.</hi> 18.) for not rooting out the Popiſh Religion, but giving their Power to the Beaſt and lying under his yoke, <hi>drunk with the Wine of his fornication.</hi> And the Hiſtorian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of <hi>Galba,,</hi> though he were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent of much harm which paſſed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153887:42"/>under his Name, yet becauſe he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to do it, whom he ought to have reſtrained, loſt both his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and open'd a way for his deſtruction. In the days of <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> the <hi>Arrians</hi> were grown very bold, through his connivance, and not only had their Aſſemblies in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> the chief City of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, but would diſpute their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>etiam in foro,</hi> and no man could prevail with the Emperour to lay a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon them, becauſe he thought it unmerciful and too ſevere ſo to do. But, <hi>qui peccata non corripit aliena, facit ſua;</hi> i. e. he that having Power, corrects not the faults of others, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts them to himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By <hi>Opinion,</hi> maintaining and teaching evil. Thus the Papiſts ſin, who generally Canonize ſuch Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> before them, encouraged the People to ſin, <hi>making void the Commandments of God, and teaching the traditions of men,</hi> Mark 7.9. In the days of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153887:43"/>of <hi>England,</hi> we read of great hatred between the two great Dukes of <hi>France, Orleance</hi> and <hi>Burgundy;</hi> this latter cauſed <hi>Orleance</hi> to be ſlain; an odious fact; yet Doctor <hi>Petit</hi> wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both Scripture and Hiſtory, to juſtifie the murther: the like were Dr. <hi>Shaa</hi> and <hi>Pinkie,</hi> one before, the other after the Coronation of <hi>Richard</hi> the Uſurper. It is a bad cauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that finds no Abettors. Moſt pertinent is that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,
<note place="margin">Fuller <hi>in his unfort. Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian.</hi>
                     </note> who Characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing <hi>Baſilius,</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Andronicus,</hi> ſaith, they were Chaplain and Patron well met; for, what one made a <hi>Law</hi> by his <hi>liſt,</hi> the other endeavoured to make Goſpel by his Learning. In ſtating any Controverſie, <hi>Baſilius</hi> firſt ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to find what <hi>Andronicus</hi> intended, or deſired to do therein, then let <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilius</hi> alone to draw that Scripture which would nor come of it ſelf, to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153887:43"/>prove the lawfulneſs of what the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would practiſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By <hi>Preſence,</hi> favouring and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting unto Evil. He that conſents, though but in his thoughts to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fraud, is a <hi>Felon</hi> before God. <hi>Paul</hi> before his Converſion was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to the death of <hi>Stephen;</hi> but afterwards he pleaded guilty of the murther. When men hear laſcivious ſtories, or ſinful-witty jeſtings and Tales of ſly ſubtle Cheats, ſecretly applauding, do partake with them. They that have an heart in the ſin, have alſo an hand in the ſin. Yea, it is poſſible for the approver to be more guilty than the Actor. The greateſt guilt comes from the full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Will. Thus <hi>Pilate</hi> allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed evil by condemning Chriſt, however he waſhed his hands and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the contrary; for after he had ſo many times declared him inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, he could not give judgment without proteſting himſelf to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. And ſo the Lord <hi>Cromwel</hi> in the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153887:44"/>Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, when by the inſtigation of Biſhop <hi>Gardiner,</hi> he was compelled by the King to read the ſentence of death againſt Mr. <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> the <hi>Martyr of Jeſus;</hi> whereof he afterward repented and craved for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. By <hi>indifferency</hi> and neutrality. As <hi>Lucian,</hi> who was no Papiſt, nor ſound Proteſtant; and <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, who deſpiſed the old Religion and envied the new. This, ſome in ſtrange Language call <hi>Policy,</hi> but in true En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh flat <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> As they in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> were neither for <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> but pretended for Chriſt, ſo theſe are neither Papiſts nor Proteſtants, a mungrel People, juſt nothing. Serve God they will, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> engage for him. Like <hi>Heraclius</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mperour, who being imprudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carried away by ſome Biſhops of the <hi>Monethelites,</hi> when that Hereſie was afterward condemn'd by the Council of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was aſhamed to recant, became a meer <hi>Neutraliſt,</hi>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:153887:44"/>and held neither one way or other. Such would be called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but they <hi>depart</hi> from nothing, nor do any thing whereby others might ſee what they were: they will be and do, as the time and Company ſerve where they live or are; Profeſſors among Profeſſors, ſcorners with ſcorners; they can change which way and when they pleaſe, without imputation of inconſtancy. On all ſuch that ſpeech of our Saviour falls heavy; they may hear the ſentence of the ſupreme Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and the King of Kings thundering in their Ears, <hi>viz. He that is not with me, is againſt me; and he that gathers not, ſcatters abroad.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To <hi>name the name of Chriſt,</hi> is to ſubmit our Wills, to be ruled by his Word, to ſubſcribe to the Goſpel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> write our ſelves his, to be under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Government of the Eternal La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>; which if we once do, we muſt <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. From falſe Gods; not worſhip dead <hi>Gods,</hi> Images, Relicks; nor dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:153887:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>Gods, men or Princes; as the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans</hi> worſhipped <hi>Antiochus Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes,</hi> ſtiling him <hi>the mighty God;</hi> or as the <hi>Venetians</hi> petitioning <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, gave him the Title of <hi>Vice-God:</hi> nor the hoſt of Heaven, as the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> nor the Devil as the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> nor the Croſs as Papiſts.</p>
                  <p>From Idolaters and Idolatrous ſervice. <hi>Come out from her my People,</hi> Revel. 18.4. If <hi>Rome</hi> have left us in the <hi>foundation,</hi> we muſt leave her in the ſuperſtructure; where they are fallen from God, we muſt fall from them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. From the familiar ſociety of ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous wicked men, (Chriſts Doves will be ſullied among the Pots), with all known impiety; yea, from evil thoughts in endeavour and earneſt deſire of our hearts, with theſe and the like, the Name of Chriſt agrees not. St. <hi>John</hi> would not remain in the Bath at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> becauſe <hi>Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus</hi> the Heretick was there. <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp</hi> would not ſalute <hi>Marcion,</hi> but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153887:45"/>told him, he knew him to be the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born of the Devil, as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> relates it; and giveth this Note alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Apoſtles, that they could not ſo much as <hi>Verbo tenus</hi> converſe with them that had adulterated the truth. There muſt be no harmony where the chief Muſician will have a jar. We have as dear a Saviour as they had; we name the ſame Chriſt they did; but we want the courage and zeal they had: moſt of us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult our own profit and pleaſure, or to gain reputation with and content others, and ſo concern our ſelves little to what company we joyn our ſelves, what we ſay or do; when indeed, the general name of Chriſtianity will avail us nothing, without <hi>departing from iniquity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is a threefold departing from iniquity, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Apparent</hi> only; when men are good in publick Profeſſion, in word and ſhew; but for their actions gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, indeed and in truth are quite
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153887:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>naught. Theſe ſet a Crown of glory upon the head of Chriſt by Profeſſion, and plat a Crown of thorns for his head, by an evil Converſation. They adore Religion by their lips, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn it not by their lives. Theſe are nominal Chriſtians; <hi>Chriſtiani ſine Chriſto,</hi> as <hi>Salvian</hi> ſpake: If their lives and Chriſts Laws were compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, their moſt ſolemn Vows and moſt perfidious violations of it, it might be confidently concluded, <hi>aut hoec non eſt lex Chriſti, aut illi non ſunt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani:</hi> and ſo <hi>Tertullian, Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> and other Antients are bold to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm of ſuch men, that they are not Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Conſtrainedly;</hi> which may be done two ways:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, By <hi>Authority.</hi> When for fear of man only, without any reſpect to God or Conſcience, men depart from heretical Societies and erroneous O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions; or from ſome foul ſins, puniſhable by Law: as, murther, ſtealing, polygamie, abominable ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153887:46"/>profanation of the Lords day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe they may depart from for fear of puniſhment by men; the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate being conſtituted by God, to be a <hi>terrour againſt evil doers.</hi> Deſire in the heart, may ſpur on ſuch a man to ſin, yet at the ſame time, <hi>fear</hi> as a Curben-bit, may check and reſtrain him: ſo that it is not the ſting of the Serpent he fears, but only its crookedneſs. Inward deſire and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſtraint are not inconſiſtent. In <hi>Calvins</hi> Epiſtle, mention is made of ſome, that out of an inordinate love of the World, made it a caſe.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>Whether or no, they might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Popiſh Religion, frequent the Popiſh worſhip, ſo that they kept the true faith only in Chriſt for juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and looked on thoſe Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ways as unprofitable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>aſh?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> To whom he replyed; that they asked counſel of him, even as <hi>Balaam</hi> conſulted with God, as if he would willingly have known his mind about curſing of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> when his
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153887:47"/>heart was ſet wholly to it, what ever God ſaid, though he were outwardly reſtrained.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Through want of <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> or perſonal ability to follow ſome kind of ſins. The Gun-powder makes no noiſe, till the fire be put to it; and the Clock ſtands ſtill till the Weights are put on: Let a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation come, which is like the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of the Weights, and the heart goes on as faſt in ſin as ever. The Sinner may not be able to maintain the trade of ſin any longer; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer is grown old, but like the aged Huntſ-man, though he cannot run, yet will hollow after the Dogs, he hath as good mind to it as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: the Drunkard is grown poor, but his heart is to ſin though his hand fail h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Theſe depart not from ſin, ſin departs from them. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are conſtrain'd to depart from one ſin to another, which is <hi>mutatio in aliud,</hi> not <hi>in melius,</hi> only a change, no leaving.</p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:153887:47"/>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Voluntary,</hi> when men, neither conſtrained meerly, nor impeded by natural indiſpoſition or diſability, but may follow evil either in Opinion or Action, then to depart from both and embrace the Truth, out of knowledg of and love to it, is a mark of <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> a ſign of juſtifying Grace. Only thus much muſt neceſſarily follow, that this departure be not feignedly, with a divided heart, but <hi>ſincerely in our thoughts,</hi> univerſally and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in our ways from the willing practice of any, but eſpecially from thoſe ſins which have moſt prevailed againſt us and wherewith God hath been diſhonour'd by us: then may we be aſſured that we are laid upon <hi>the foundation of God;</hi> that the Lord from all eternity know us to be his own, and that he will not reject, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forſake us in our Perſons or Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, while we bear <hi>the name of Chriſt and depart from iniquity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whence ariſeth a ſecond Concluſion for our inſtruction, as followeth;</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="doctrine">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:153887:48"/>
               <head>Doctrine 2. <hi>That inward faith in Chriſt, joyned with an outward profeſſion of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel and an holy Converſation, are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per notes and ſigns of Election.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Acts 4.12. <hi>There is no other name under heaven given among men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we can be ſaved.</hi> Chriſtians then are only capable of Salvation.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.25. Faith is made a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fruit of Gods mercy: Election is not <hi>for</hi> faith, but <hi>to</hi> faith in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Epheſ. 2.8. <hi>By grace ye are ſaved through faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Philip. 1.29. <hi>To you it is given not only to believe, but to ſuffer for Chriſts ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Epheſ. 1.4. <hi>He hath choſen us in him from before the foundation of the world, that we ſhould be holy and without blame before him in Love.</hi> Holineſs of Life then, a departing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:153887:48"/>from iniquity, is a ſure ſign of <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. For, 1. Elected we are in Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>That in the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the fulneſs of time, he might gather together in one, all things in Chriſt, — In whom we have obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being predeſtinate according to the purpoſe of him who worketh all things according to the purpoſe of his Will,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Elected we are to Faith, whoſe property it is to purifie the heart from a delight in ſin. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.29. <hi>It is given to you not only to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All the Promiſes are made to ſuch as believe and live holily. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Be thou faithful to the death, and I will give thee a Crown of life.</hi> Heb. 12.14. <hi>Follow peace and holineſs,</hi> &amp;c. Holineſs is the only Coyn which paſſeth current in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Having ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c. Beſides that bright Cloud of Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153887:49"/>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. who through faith and holineſs obtained a laſting <hi>good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> and are paſs'd out of mortal Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſeparated from the contagion of earth, to the recompenſe of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, enjoying and beholding the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly harmony of the bleſſedneſſes of the Celeſtial Region, having this Seal of <hi>Election;</hi> as the ground to aſſure them of Salvation, whilſt they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant amongſt men dwelling in Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of clay.</p>
               <p>All they who were fore-known by the Lord to be in <hi>the foundation,</hi> were certainly alſo pre-ordained to the means for the execution. It is a wicked Argument, which ſome make to themſelves, as Hereticks and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal men did in St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> time, and the like is reported of <hi>Lewis</hi> the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh of <hi>France,</hi> who deſperately argued, <hi>Si ſalvabor, ſalvabor; ſi ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò damnabor, damnabor; if I ſhall be ſaved, I ſhall be ſaved, however I live, whatever I do.</hi> A moſt daring infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; 'tis to ſuck Poiſon out of a
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:153887:49"/>ſweet flower, to kindle Hell out of a ſpark of Truth, to daſh againſt the <hi>Rock of Ages,</hi> to fall into the Pit, which was digged for better purpoſe, to <hi>ſtumble at the Word, whereunto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they were appointed.</hi> If all Perſons ſhould ſo argue, who ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? who would ſet his face towards Heaven? for the ſame Curtain that hides Ordination to life and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from one, doth hide it from all, till that Curtain be drawn and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers it to ſhine upon ſome in the uſe of means: For certain it is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The wiſdom of God never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined the end, but it alſo deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the means: and as the <hi>end</hi> is alway glorious, ſo the means are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver powerful and efficacious; and none can more chearfully demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate their tendency and proximity to the end, than thoſe who are moſt careful in a ſeaſonable and thankful ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the means; and it will be found a ſelf-deceiving practice, a ſnare for ſuch who entangle themſelves
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153887:50"/>with ſuch a deſperate fallacy as the Argument forms.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is a prepoſterous way to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute from the leſs known to the more known. As if a man ſhould get on the higheſt Round of the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der firſt. We have no Scripture-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to peep into thoſe hidden Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of Eternity, to ſpell our names in the Stars. Gods everlaſting De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, is too dazling and ſplendid an Object for us at firſt to ſet our Eyes upon: it is far eaſier and ſafer for us to look upon the Rays of his goodneſs, as they are reflected in our own hearts, and there to take pleaſure in reading the mild and gentle Characters of Divine Love to us, in our love to him and our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere compliance with his Heavenly Will; as it is more ſafe for us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the twinkling beauty of that Radiant, heavenly Body the Sun, as it is fairly reflected in ſome Cryſtal ſtream, than to caſt up our daring Eyes upon the body thereof, which
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:153887:50"/>is too bright and ſcorching for us. We muſt go to the means, which are beſt known unto us, and not unto Gods Decree and fore-knowledg, which is <hi>ſealed.</hi> The Windows of the Soul muſt be ſet open for the entertaining ſuch light as doth more immediately flow in upon it; and the Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding muſt cloſe with ſuch Objects as are beſt proportionable to it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Peter</hi> directs (if we account his Method obſervable and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom) to make <hi>calling</hi> and then <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> ſure; as thus, if we be effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called and juſtified by faith in Chriſt, if we hate all ſin, make Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of all our ways, if we deſire to live in the fear of the Lord, at all times and this without Hypocriſie, then <hi>may</hi> we be aſſur'd of our <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> and certainly, that's the beſt aſſurance of any mans intereſt in God, which is founded upon confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to him: as when we ſee the fruits of the Earth ſpringing up, we conclude the Sun hath been there;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:153887:51"/>ſo if we find the fruits of Holineſs ſpringing up in our hearts, we may conclude the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> hath riſen there. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>God hath choſen you from the beginning to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, by the ſanctification of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> No calculation of <hi>Election,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sanctification. God indeed in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us, begins at the higheſt links of the Chain; but we muſt begin at the loweſt link and ſo aſcend higher. Faith in Chriſt, joyned with a holy Life, are infallible ſigns of <hi>Election.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I.</head>
                  <p>Whence we may learn,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What Chriſtianity is, <hi>viz. A naming the name of Chriſt and depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from iniquity.</hi> Profeſſion and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Chriſt's Goſpel. Where one of theſe are without the other, there, men are but <hi>almoſt</hi> Chriſtians; in <hi>name,</hi> not in deed; half Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>There are three ſorts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians:</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:153887:51"/>
                  <p n="1">1. In <hi>name</hi> only; of whom it may be ſaid, as they do of the Cinnamon Tree, that the bark is more worth than all they have beſides. Of theſe we read, 1 <hi>Titus</hi> 16. <hi>They profeſs that they know God, but in works they deny him.</hi> Such are your mired Worldlings, glittering Hypocrites, ſwiniſh Epicures. Theſe are abuſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Chriſtians, without Chriſt; they are Chriſtians to the reproach of Chriſt, <hi>Si Chriſtus ſancta docuiſſet, à Chriſtianis ſancta fierent: qualis Secta, tales Sectatores. Quomodo bonus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter, cujus tam pravos videmus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipulos?</hi> as <hi>Lactantius</hi> brings in the the Heathen upbraiding the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Actions. Such is the malice lodg'd in the hearts of degenerated Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which will reproach the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitude of the Rule; for the obliquity of their Lives, who ſwerve and vary from it. Yet of this ſort are too many among us; ſuch as wear Chriſts Livery, but do the Devils drudgery; <hi>Wens</hi> on the face of <hi>Religion.</hi> Their
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:153887:52"/>Profeſſion is but like a fair Glove drawn over a foul Hand, or a good Paint over a rotten Poſt, and the enamelling of a Dunghil with Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beams. They are colour'd Tombs that make only an encloſure of rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs; and no marvel if theſe fall away, they never ſaw the Seal in, or upon themſelves.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In <hi>deed</hi> only: as the believing <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> before Chriſt; Children of faithful Parents, dying before they have ability to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual profeſſion of Chriſtianity: ſuch as are born deaf and dumb, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the uſe of Reaſon. Who knows what the Divine goodneſs hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for them, or how he works in them?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In <hi>name</hi> and in <hi>deed;</hi> like Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, that have an inward worth and caſt forth a ſparkling luſtre to the Eyes of others. Theſe, as <hi>Solomons</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are Gold within and without. Such are Chriſtians of ripe years, living to know, believing what they
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:153887:52"/>know of Chriſt and profeſſing what they believe, practiſing what they profeſs: theſe are Chriſtians indeed, <hi>ſealed up unto the day of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>How may ſuch be known?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is ſealed, to <hi>ſtay</hi> ſuch cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity; either to know or make a ſeparation in our cenſure or judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before the time: infallibly to know the election of others, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to determine of their inward di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition, by ſome few things, we hear or ſee, is impoſſible. Such are known to themſelves. Yet in the judgment of Charity, we take all ſuch to be the Lords, who make a good Profeſſion, frequent Ordinances, practice Piety in their Houſes. And further, what hath God revealed to us, it is lawful for us to ſay, we know. Chriſt hath told us, <hi>by their fruits ye ſhall know them:</hi> as by the leaves the Tree is ſeen, ſo by the fruit the Tree is known. All Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have their ſeveral Eſſences, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:153887:53"/>according to the eſſence ſo are the actings. Stars that are placed in the higheſt Orb ſhine brighteſt. The hand of the Dial is without in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as the Wheels of the Clock are within in going; as where the heart is of a good Conſtitution, the life will be of a fair Complexion. When the Conduit is walled in, how ſhall we judg of the Spring, but by the Water that runs out of the Pipes.</p>
                  <p>True Chriſtians, ſuch as are laid upon <hi>the foundation of God,</hi> may be known, by theſe following marks or fruits:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Humility;</hi> an unſeparable badg of true Chriſtianity. It is the great Grace; the Crown and varniſh of every grace. Of all men, the humble Saint on Earth, looks likeſt to a Citizen of Heaven. The choiſeſt Wines are laid up in the loweſt Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. Like your Spire Steeples, the true Saint is <hi>minimus in ſummo,</hi> ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt where it is higheſt; or as thoſe Orient Stars, which are leſs viewed,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:153887:53"/>the higher they are placed. No Gold ſo pure, as that which is moſt ductile, and that's the beſt Blade which bends well, without reteining its crooked figure. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> being asked, which was the firſt Grace? anſwered, <hi>Humility.</hi> Which, the ſecond &amp; third? he anſwer'd, <hi>Humility.</hi> Empty Casks ſound moſt, when the well fraught Veſſel, ſilenceth its own fulneſs: and the deep Rivers pay larger tribute to the Sea, than the ſhallow brooks, and yet empty themſelves without noiſe. Thus it goes with the heirs of Heaven. As the Harp, though they ſound moſt ſweetly, they hear not their own melody. As Violets cover themſelves with their leaves, ſo do gracious Perſons hide their ſweeteſt Excellencies, under the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of humility. They live, yet not they, but Chriſt liveth in them. They are willing to be a Cypher, ſo Chriſt may ſtand for a figure, <hi>Pror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Satan eſt Lutherus, ſed vivat &amp; regnat Chriſtus;</hi> Let <hi>Luther</hi> be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:153887:54"/>a Devil, ſo Chriſt may be exalted as God; ſaith that Incarnate <hi>Seraphim</hi> of himſelf. They ſay, in Herauldry, the plaineſt Coats are the richeſt Arms; ſure we may be, the moſt <hi>poor in ſpirit</hi> on Earth, are the richeſt Citizens of Heaven. This they learn of their Maſter, at their entrance into his School; to be meek and lowly in heart, both in regard of God and man.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Love;</hi> that is a Jewel Chriſts Bride wears; a ſparkling Diamond, which God placeth in the boſom of his Elect: 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.16. <hi>He that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God.</hi> As there is Love deſcending to us, ſo there is Love aſcending to God. It's ſaid, that Iron touched with a Loadſtone, it hath an inclination of following the Loadſtone; verily, when God hath touched any ſoul with his Love, it leaves an inſtinct behind it, of following after God. And where this Love dwells, it is operative; like fire (for it's a Divine flame), it is
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:153887:54"/>not idle but active, and it works di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſſy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Towards the Word of God. This is given as the mark of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; <hi>Pſalm</hi> 1.2. <hi>His delight is in the Law of God.</hi> The Prophet <hi>David</hi> often expreſſeth ſo much. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>O how I love thy Law? how ſweet are thy words to my taſte? yea, ſweeter than the honey to my mouth; dearer unto me than thouſands of gold and ſilver.</hi> He roles it as Sugar under his Tongue; he takes pleaſure in it, as a man doth in a bed of Roſes. The covetous man takes great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in telling his thouſands; but <hi>David</hi> hath ſweeter apprehenſions and affections to Gods Law, than he had to thouſands. And ſo the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Ch. 15. v. 16. <hi>Thy words were ſound and I did eat them;</hi> and <hi>thy word was unto me the joy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing of my heart.</hi> To the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Ch. 60. v. 8. <hi>Who are theſe that fly as a Cloud and as Doves to their windows?</hi> Gracious
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:153887:55"/>ſouls fly as Doves to an Ordinance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Wings of Love. God opens the heart of his Choſen to love the Word; to receive it as new born Babes do the milk of the Breaſt; greedily, delightfully, patiently, and profitably to grow thereby. And therefore <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, ſpeaking of wicked men, <hi>only contemn not the Word and there is hope.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>To this ſome or other may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; I love the Word and have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from it, though I be not ſo ſtrickt and curious for my life, as others are.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is impoſſible for a man to love the Word, and not reform his life by it. <hi>David</hi> gave not only his Ear, but turned his Feet to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God. He <hi>walked</hi> in them. We judg not of a mans health by his high Colour, but by the pulſe of the Arm; ſo we judg not of a Chriſtians ſoundneſs by <hi>words;</hi> what are they but an higher colour? but by his obedient actings towards God,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:153887:55"/>and when we ſee his Soul tuned into a conformity with his Word and mans Will, ſo far as it is diſcernable, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to concur with Gods Will. Hear the Divine Apoſtle, who wrote his Epiſtles with an Ear in Heaven, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.3. <hi>By this we know, that we know him</hi> (and by this we know that we love him) <hi>if we keep his Commandments. John</hi> 14.21. <hi>He hath hath my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me.</hi> John, Epiſt. 2. v. 6. <hi>This is Love, that we walk in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments?</hi> Peter, <hi>Loveſt thou me, feed my Lambs.</hi> The Cryſtal ſtreams of Divine Actions, will neceſſarily bubble from the pure ſpring of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> This Love works towards the Meſſengers, which bring <hi>the glad tidings of ſalvation</hi> to us. They that love the Meſſage, cannot but mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it, by a tender expreſſion of love to the Meſſengers. How welcom are the feet of thoſe, who bring glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings from <hi>Emmanuels Land,</hi> the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:153887:56"/>Countrey of <hi>Canaan?</hi> He it enjoyn'd, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.29. <hi>Receive them with all gladneſs and hold ſuch in reputation.</hi> 1 Theſſal. 5. <hi>Eſteem them very highly in love,</hi> (if not for their own, yet) <hi>for their works ſake.</hi> Miniſters are Gods Angels, to ſet forth the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God and eternal Life, (<hi>non ſpecie oeſtimandi ſed munere;</hi>) not to be judg'd of by their outſide, but by their Office; as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> expreſſeth it. The moſt curious Pearls are here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed in the ruggeſt ſhells; and the Lord lodgeth rich Treaſures in earthen Veſſels. See Turks &amp; Idolatrous Papiſts honouring every hedg-Prieſt of theirs, and have them in ſingular eſteem, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their merits: and it is obſerv'd of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> how they gave grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſpect to their Philoſophers than to their Oratours, becauſe theſe taught them only how to ſpeak, but they how to live well. Let us learn ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from them, to love faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, who labour with Chriſt in the Goſpel. It is a good ſign and cannot miſs a Reward.</p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:153887:56"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It works towards the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt, our fellow-ſervants; Profeſſours of Religion in the Power thereof; of whom we may and ought to have this hope, that they are laid with us in the <hi>foundation of God.</hi> This ſweet Spice ſends forth its ſmell that bears his Image, on whom it contemplateth the Image of the firſt Beauty, <hi>John</hi> 13.35. <hi>By this ſhall all men know ye are my Diſciples, if ye have love one to another.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens diſciples are known by their Titles, Habits, Ceremonies, as the Popes Shavelings are: but <hi>Love</hi> is Chriſts cognizance. <hi>He who loveth him who begets, loveth him alſo that is begotten.</hi> Gods Children are his walking Pictures; if we love God, we ſhall love thoſe on whom he hath drawn his Image; yea, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome infirmities; as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren love one another, though there be ſome imperfections of Nature; and we love Gold in the Oar, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding its Droſſineſs. The beſt Saints
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:153887:57"/>have their blemiſhes; the faireſt Face may have a ſcar to diſgrace it. Yea, though poor, the Children of God love their Fathers Image, though hung in never ſo mean a Frame. Though we have not grace or gifts in that meaſure and degree we ſee it in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet if we love it in them and them for it, we may be confident, God hath begun his work in us. None can prize Grace, but they that have it. Love of grace is the beginning of grace. Love of good men with an expreſſion of it according to ability, is a ſign of ſpiritual goodneſs. It is a moſt dangerous thing to be at enmity with thoſe who love God; to ſlight or oppoſe them in their gracious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours: yet our Saviour hath fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told it; <hi>In the latter days, iniquity ſhall abound and the love of many ſhall wax cold.</hi> Where ſin reigns, there is no Love.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Conſtancy in good: profeſſing and <hi>ſo perfecting holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> They are compared to <hi>Palm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees,</hi>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:153887:57"/>becauſe they flouriſh ſoon; to <hi>Cedar,</hi> becauſe they continue long. The true Saint, like <hi>Coeſar,</hi> is alway marching forward. Travellers that go to Sea, meerly to be Sea-ſick, if a black Cloud or ſtorm ariſe, their Voyage is ended, home they get to the Harbour; they went not forth to be Weather-beaten, or to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves among the boiſterous billows, but only for pleaſure. But the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, that is bound for a Voyage, whoſe Calling it is, is not daunted at the ſurging Waves and fierce Winds, but drives through with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. They that pretend only to <hi>Religion,</hi> if a ſtorm meet them in the way to Heaven, leave the way, take ſhelter in the Earth; as a Snail, they put out their heads to ſee what wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is abroad (what countenance <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> hath among thoſe whoſe names are written in greater Letters than others are) and if the Heavens frown, they ſhrink into the ſhell; eſteeming that their happineſs. But ſuch as
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:153887:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>make <hi>Religion</hi> their buſineſs, ſteer not their courſe by ſuch Cards; they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Trade, though they meet with many Tryals. The ſcorching Sun of Perſecution, burns not up the flower of true Devotion. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.6. <hi>He that hath begun a good work in you, will perform it, until the day of Chriſt.</hi> Like a well-drawn Picture, they have always the ſame Viſage; or rather, as the Deity, they continue one and the ſame Action; as Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cannot charm them, ſo neither can Adverſity find Darts that are able to abate their Chriſtian reſolution. Theſe flowers of Paradiſe wither not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe watered from Heaven. Blazing Comets may fall to the Earth, but fixed Stars remain in their Orb: Grace may be ſhaken in the Soul, but ſhall never be ſhaken out of the Soul. If any Candles have been put out, it was becauſe they were not carried in Chriſts Lanthorn.</p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee the ſparklings of this matchleſs Diamond, the plain work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:153887:58"/>of this grace of <hi>Election;</hi> Thus do the ſacred Writings ſet forth the beauty and oriency of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. Hence divers are condemned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Jews,</hi> with all uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted <hi>Gentiles;</hi> who though they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from ſome Evils, yet they <hi>name not the name of Chriſt;</hi> that's to the <hi>Jews a ſtumbling-block and to the Greeks fooliſhneſs,</hi> 1 Cor, 1.23. As for the <hi>Jews,</hi> they pitching in their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon a glorious Prince, who ſhould free them from the <hi>Roman</hi> yoak; would not ſo endure to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed, as inſtead thereof to have a crucified man, one in the form of a ſervant to be their <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would not that he ſhould reign over them, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.4. and as for the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> judging it <hi>a fooliſh</hi> thing to expect <hi>life</hi> from <hi>a dead</hi> man, and <hi>Glory</hi> from one who kept not himſelf from <hi>ſhame,</hi> and hearing Doctrines
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:153887:59"/>wholly inconſiſtent with what they had ſucked in, did therefore refuſe to ſubmit to Chriſt. But woe be to them that ſtumble at this ſtone; if Chriſt be not the <hi>Riſing,</hi> he will be for the <hi>fall</hi> of men. No Diſeaſe ſo fatal, as that which rejecteth Cordials: No ſtate ſo deſperate as that which thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away Salvation; <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Papiſts; who under the name of Chriſt, rob him of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; renounce his <hi>Free-grace,</hi> and will not endure to be ſhut out from all cauſility towards their own Salvation, affirming their works of <hi>Condignity</hi> and <hi>Congruity</hi> to diſpoſe them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him. They like not to hear of Diſcriminating-grace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> All <hi>Verbal</hi> Profeſſors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; that profeſs they <hi>know Chriſt, but in their works deny him, being diſobedient, abominable, and to every good work reprobate.</hi> And theſe are either Speakers or Hearers.</p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:153887:59"/>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Speakers;</hi> who are Catholick in Preaching, and heretical in Living; having Chriſt in the <hi>Book</hi> but not in the <hi>Heart;</hi> ſpeaking like <hi>Balaams</hi>-Aſs to the underſtanding of others, but not to their own; as the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Dunce, the idle Drone, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Worldling, ſwyniſh Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, prophane Swearer, the riotous miſpender of time, with Cards and Dice, Hawks and Hounds; which were once not thought fit Books for the <hi>Clergy;</hi> the uſurious <hi>Symoniſt</hi> and ambitious Non-reſident: who pull down more, in ſix days, than they, with many more and better, can build up in a year. I am loath to draw a line in any mans Picture with a black Coal; yet how many of this colour are there to be ſeen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very-where? It is monſtrous, as <hi>Bernard</hi> truly told <hi>Eugenius,</hi> that men ſhould have the higheſt ſeat in the Church, and the baſeſt life out of the Church. Certainly, it is a
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:153887:60"/>great miſery, that they ſhould have many Souls committed to their truſt and keeping, who cannot keep one, and that their own. Theſe are Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians who give Cordials to others, and faint themſelves. They are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Stars,</hi> which are the Ornament of the Heavens, becauſe they ſhould be the Ornament of the Church; but by their ſpotted and beleopar'd lives, they prove not <hi>Stars,</hi> but <hi>ſtains</hi> and blemiſhes of the Church. They are called <hi>Salt;</hi> but <hi>if the ſalt have loſt its ſavour, wherewith ſhall it be ſeaſoned?</hi> This hinders the converſion of People. Hence they exclaim, <hi>How can freſh and ſalt water flow from the ſame fountain?</hi> they loath thoſe wholeſom Truths taught, as men loath good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Meat, when it comes out of a foul Diſh, or as men like not the light of a Candle, when ſet on a ſluttiſh Candleſtick. Thus <hi>Elies</hi> ſons made the People abhor <hi>the Offerings
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:153887:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Lord,</hi> by their wicked lives, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.7. Such cauſe the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels of the Church to wither in their hands, they defile her Victories, ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe her Lights, and ſo become Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in the Church of God; yea, fiery Torches to enflame his Temple; and as falſe Lights on the ſhoar, they lead Ships to Sands and Rocks to ſplit them. I have read of a Gentlewoman who turned Atheiſt, becauſe ſhe lived under the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a great Doctor, that taught well, but lived licentiouſly; It was he (ſaid ſhe) that conjur'd up thoſe damnable thoughts in my Soul. <hi>Words bluſh where deeds do fail. Phyſician heal thy ſelf.</hi> He that ſmites ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a wounded Arm; alas, he ſmites but faintly; becauſe whileſt he ſmites another, he bleeds himſelf. <hi>Lucian</hi> the Apothecary made himſelf ridiculous, by ſelling a Medicine to cure the Cough in others, but cured not himſelf: Thus he that reproves
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:153887:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>another of what himſelf is guilty, foameth out his own ſhame. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, they hinder their own Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Among all others, the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Miniſter is a matter of great difficulty; according to that ſharp ſpeech of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> one of the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Preachers that ever ſpake; <hi>Few Miniſters ſhould be ſaved:</hi> With ſuch the Lord expoſtulates the matter, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 50.16. <hi>What haſt thou to do to take my word within thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt to be reformed? Thou that ſayeſt a man ſhould not ſteal, do'ſt thou ſteal?</hi> Rom. 2. The Eyes of all are upon ſuch; they who are blind as Moles in their own Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, have the Eyes of a Lynx to eſpy your aberrations. Miniſters muſt Practiſe as well as Preach Holineſs, or they mar all. A flaw in the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, robs it of its orient ſplendor: a Fly in the Apothecaries box, ſpoils the fragrancy of its Odour; thus it is here.</p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:153887:61"/>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Hearers;</hi> that profeſs and ſpeak well; having Chriſt often in their Ears and upon their Tongue, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in their Hearts and Hands. Theſe carry a bright Light in a Dark-Lanthorn; build their Neſts among the Stars, and make their Bed in Hell. It is better not to ſhine, than not to be Gold, to be Profeſſours of Piety and Practitioners of iniquity is a palpable contradiction; a golden Tongue and a leaden Heart never matched together. It will prove no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for any one to have the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet on his Lip, who hath not the Torch in his Hand. <hi>Why call ye me Lord and do not the things that I ſay?</hi> Such ſhall be miſerably reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. <hi>Tamberlain</hi> in his Wars would not own a pot of Gold dig'd out of the Earth and preſented to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it had not his Fathers ſtamp. Certainly, God will own none but thoſe who have the ſtamp of Chriſt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:153887:62"/>on their Actions. The ill deportment of ſome who paſs for Chriſtians, hath made men afraid to embrace Religion. Hence ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Pagans of old ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped back,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fullers Holy War,</hi> p. 88.</note> who had one foot in the Church, when they ſaw Chriſtians, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved ſo well, live ſo ill, breaking the <hi>Commandments</hi> againſt the <hi>Creed.</hi> And as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſpake of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of the Church in his time, <hi>viz.</hi> if a <hi>Gentile</hi> ſhould come and ſay, I would be a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> yet when he ſees ſuch a Spirit of diſſention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, one of <hi>Paul</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Apollo,</hi> ſuch are their diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, that he knows not which to chooſe, but muſt return to his <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliſm</hi> again; the ſame may be ſaid of the lives of many profeſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; others will be apt to think, that <hi>Religion</hi> is no more than a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout complement; a ſevere Policy. <hi>Practice</hi> doth ſpeak louder than Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:153887:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>only; as the Emperour <hi>Jovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> told the Orthodox and <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhops, <hi>I cannot judg of your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; but I can judg of your Lives.</hi> Practice of Holineſs is a powerful Loadſtone to draw others to a love of Holineſs. <hi>Baſil</hi> obſerves, that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> in one of his Epiſtles writing to <hi>Arſatius,</hi> ſaith, that the Chriſtian Religion did flouriſh by the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and liberality of them who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed it. Wo be to them, who by their irregular practices, render it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious! You were all born to ſerve God; and better you had never been born, than not to ſerve him unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly and univerſally. As <hi>A. Fulvius</hi> ſaid to his Son, when he found him in <hi>Catalines</hi> Conſpiracy; <hi>Non ego te Catalinae genui, ſed Patriae;</hi> thus the Lord ſaith to every man, I gave you not a Soul, incomparable, more precious than the Purple and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Kings, to ſuffer it to wallow in the filthineſs of the fleſh, and make
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:153887:63"/>it an inſtrument of ſenſuality, a Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of Abomination, wherein to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it as a ſacrifice to the Devil. God will one day pluck the Viſard from your Face and ſay, All true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans I know, <hi>but who are ye?</hi> Why did you take my Name upon you and not depart from ſin? <hi>depart from me ye workers of iniquity.</hi> Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew 7.23. O conſider this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, all ye that are Chriſtians in <hi>Name,</hi> but Atheiſts in <hi>Practice!</hi> What wiſedom is it to be trimming the Scabbard, whileſt the Sword is ruſting? to have a name only to live and yet be dead? A pompous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion without ſuitable Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is worth nothing. Conſider I ſay, and the Lord <hi>give you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in all things.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:153887:63"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> III.</head>
                  <p n="3">3. This Doctrine offers matter of ſingular comfort to all true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, a ſovereign Cordial to revive and maintain their fainting ſpirits, under all fears and cares about per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering to the end of their War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare; who find the Seal of <hi>Election</hi> in themſelves, by examining and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Premiſſes; Who <hi>name the name of Chriſt and depart from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> You are part of <hi>Gods build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> whoſe <hi>foundation is ſure.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all your failings, he'l give ſtrength to bring forth. The bruiſed Reed ſhall be turned into a brazen Serpent, and the ſmoaking Flax into a triumphant Flame. Chriſt's errand from Heaven to Earth was, not only to kindle a Divine Life; but alſo to propagate this Celeſtial Fire unto Perfection. He was never
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:153887:64"/>abſent from this ſpark of Divinity in any poor Sinners breaſt. He is an inexhauſtible Fountain of ſpiritual life, and ever toucheth any poor Soul enliven'n'd with it, by an out-ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ray, and freely lends his beams and diſperſeth his influences unto it from the beginning to the ending. What ever change you may find in your ſelves, or in any Creature, you ſhall find an eternal Identity in God. As there is no ſhadow of turning in his <hi>Being,</hi> ſo not in his <hi>Love.</hi> Here is no vertical Point. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.7. <hi>With everlaſting kindneſs will I have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>But how can a child of God, wholly depart from iniquity; ſeeing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but death can divide ſin from the Soul?</hi> Rom. 6.7. He that is dead is freed from ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Sin is to be conſidered two ways:</p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:153887:64"/>
                  <p n="1">1. As <hi>being</hi> in and with our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: ſo, we cannot be free from it here, in our mortal Eſtate, whil'ſt blood is in our Veins, ſin will be in our nature. When the Body and Soul is ſeparated by mortality, ſin and the Soul ſhall be ſeparated to Eternity. Though in the living man Luſt is mortified. Sin like <hi>Sampſons</hi> hair, though it be cut, it will grow again and come to its ſtrength: as the feathers of a Fowl, pluck them off, they will come forth again, only kill the Bird and they grow no more.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As <hi>reigning</hi> in us and obeyed by us in the luſt thereof; ſo we may and muſt depart from it here, or elſe we ſhall never ſee the Lord with comfort hereafter. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Let not ſin reign in your mortal bodies,</hi> &amp;c. Heb. 12.14. <hi>Follow peace with all men and holineſs, without which, no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:153887:65"/>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>But ſuppoſe a man depart once from all ſin reigning in him, will not his after-commiſſion of ſin, annihilate and extinguiſh his former departure?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> A man may leave ſin, only from a principle of morality; as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon</hi> mentioned by St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> who being an Infidel, a young man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the knowledg of the true God, reſigned over to all ſort of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance; Wine, love and play with Raſhneſs, were the Chariot, which drew him to his downfal; but hearing <hi>Socrates</hi> to read an Ethick Lecture of Vertue and Vice, went away changed and no more followed his exorbitances; and ſome others, as <hi>Cato, Seneca, Ariſtides,</hi> with divers others ſparking-brave Souls among the <hi>Romans,</hi> who ſeeing a beauty in Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, became renowned for their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent deportments. From this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, <hi>Scipio</hi> an Heathen and a Soldier
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:153887:65"/>too, would not permit certain Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Virgins of exquiſite beauty, to be brought into his Preſence, <hi>Ne quid de Virginitatis integritate delibaſſe, ſaltèm vel oculis videretur,</hi> as <hi>Florus</hi> ſaith; <hi>i. e.</hi> that he might not ſeem to have ſipt the honour of their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, ſo much as with beholding them. A man may leave one ſin and take up another which ſutes bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with his Age and Place; forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſin only of deſign. How good was <hi>Joaſh,</hi> ſo long as <hi>Jehojada</hi> the Prieſt lived? The Lion may look demure; whil'ſt under invincible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint. <hi>Nero</hi> himſelf acted it very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily for the firſt five years, under the conduct of <hi>Seneca.</hi> Others hide their ſins; like thoſe who ſhut their ſhop-windows, and follow their Trade within doors: Many deal with their ſins as <hi>Moſes</hi> his Mother dealt with him; ſhe hid him in the Ark of Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſhes, as if ſhe had left him, but her Eye was ſtill upon him, and in
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:153887:66"/>concluſion ſhe became his Nurſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.9. Many hide their ſins from the Eyes of others, when their hearts go after them, and at laſt they give the breaſt unto them. But what availeth ſuch a practice? A hand taken off from ſinful practices, without a heart taken off from ſinful principles, will be like a piece of ground, which when ſown again, yields more encreaſe, or like a ſtream that hath met with a damm, will run with a greater violence, when the Sluce is open'd, ſo all this comes to nothing.</p>
                  <p>But this: 1. If a man once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from ſin, out of a love to God, or fear of his Judgments and hatred of ſin; if he do this freely and heartily, <hi>after</hi>-acts of ſin through infirmity, can never annihilate ſuch a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. My reaſon is; When God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gives one ſin, he forgives all; if once,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:153887:66"/>he forgives ever. So that an act of ſin, being in and coming from a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate man, cannot diſſolve the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of juſtifying Grace. Grace was not got meerly with humane actions, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it thereby be wholly loſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. I ſay, that as wicked men may <hi>actually</hi> do that good duty, keep that Commandment for a time, which habitually they break and diſallow; ſo Regenerate men, may and do <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitually</hi> keep thoſe Commandments, which they do <hi>actually</hi> break; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do it not with a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and purpoſe. They ſtill depart from that ſin in heart, which in <hi>act</hi> they may out of neceſſary weakneſs yield unto.</p>
                  <p>Many and great are the Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Chriſt's Elect, while they <hi>name the name of Chriſt</hi> and ſtrive in the uſe of means againſt their own corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. The Lord by his Spirit powerfully works in them Victory by degrees, with aſſurance of Salvation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="application">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:153887:67"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> IV.</head>
                  <p>Laſtly, All may be hence exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Profeſſours</hi> or <hi>Prophane,</hi> and that three ways, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That you would ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of theſe two main fundamental parts of Chriſtianity; <hi>The foundation of God</hi> and <hi>aſſurance</hi> thereof; as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and ſeaſonable in theſe back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding times, wherein there are ſo many Errours and ſuch diverſity of Opinions vented; ſo much trouble felt and feared in Church and State, maugre the malice of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians,</hi> their Patrons and defenders, Men or Devils; Let the ſervants of Chriſt know, <hi>The foundation of God ſtands ſure, the Lord knoweth who are his,</hi> and they ſhall never be known to belong to any other. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, as alſo the ſigns and marks of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:153887:67"/>Election, that all may ſeek them, none may preſume of mercy without them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That you would ſpeedily begin, if you have not done it already, to lay a <hi>foundation</hi> in your ſelves, mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. <hi>Of repentance from dead works and faith towards God.</hi> The principal reaſon why many Profeſſours fall back <hi>from,</hi> or make ſuch monſtrous buildings <hi>in</hi> their Profeſſion, by idle and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs conceits, is, becauſe they began without a <hi>foundation,</hi> raſhly running with others, not conſidering why or whither. God Almighty you ſee, would do nothing without a Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, your practice muſt needs be preſumption.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That as you hope for ſalvation by Chriſt upon this <hi>foundation,</hi> you would examine your ſelves, according to the former evidences. It is report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:153887:68"/>of a famous Carver, who making a curious Image of <hi>Minerva,</hi> did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly engrave his own upon it; ſo the Lord of Heaven hath interwoven his own Image in his People, which remains as a mark whereby they may be known to be his own <hi>workmanſhip.</hi> Search it out in you: allow nothing in you, which is or may be condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by you. Let nothing be acted in one World, which cannot be anſwered in another. (They can have no hope at the general Aſſizes, whoſe Conſcience condemns them before the appearing of the Judg.) That ſo when the Lord cometh in glory, he may know you to be his own, ſealed with his Spirit, waſh'd in his Blood and cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Righteouſneſs; for whom a Crown of Righteouſneſs was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, <hi>before the foundations of the world were laid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What ſhould hinder ſuch Men and Women from aſſurance of Heaven?
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:153887:68"/>The <hi>foundation of God</hi> is laid; the ſigns of Election are ſeen, <hi>both</hi> eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſealed. <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us from from the love of Chriſt?</hi> ſhall Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan or wicked men? temptation or perſecution? poverty or death? None of all, nothing of all: for <hi>the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God ſtands ſure, having this Seal, The Lord knoweth who are his; and let every one that nameth the name of Chriſt, depart from iniquity!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Glory be to God in the Higheſt!</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153887:69"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
